<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scanderbeg redivivus an historical account of the life &amp; actions of the most victorious Prince John III, K. of Poland : containing an exact and succinct series of affairs from his cradle to this present day, with a particular account of the many great and signal victories obtained by him against the Turks, from the time he was first made crown-general, and afterwards elected King of Poland : dedicated to the Lord Landsdowne, Count of the Holy Empire.</title>
            <author>H. G.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23352</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17150080</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206299</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240863855</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G26</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">17150080</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206299)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1616:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scanderbeg redivivus an historical account of the life &amp; actions of the most victorious Prince John III, K. of Poland : containing an exact and succinct series of affairs from his cradle to this present day, with a particular account of the many great and signal victories obtained by him against the Turks, from the time he was first made crown-general, and afterwards elected King of Poland : dedicated to the Lord Landsdowne, Count of the Holy Empire.</title>
                  <author>H. G.</author>
                  <author>Hove, Frederick Hendrick van, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 155, [1], [2] leaves of plates (1 folded) : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.C. for Tho. Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to H.G.</note>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: H.G.</note>
                  <note>Engraved frontispiece portrait of the King signed: F.H. Van Houe, sculp.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages torn, with loss of print; pages 36-57 from defective Huntington Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">John --  III Sobieski, --  King of Poland, 1629-1696.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Turco-Polish Wars, 1683-1699.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Poland --  History --  John III Sobieski, 1674-1696.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:2"/>
            <head>An Account of the Standard in General.</head>
            <p>THE Standard is a Rich Embroydery of Gold and Silver; the Characters upon the Green Ground Embroyder'd with Gold, the Border upon a Red Ground Interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with Flowrings of Silver: The Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle part richly Embroyder'd with Gold upon a Red Ground. The Characters wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the Ground: The length of the Standard from the Point to the Staff, is 12 <hi>Roman</hi> Palms; the breadth of the whole, 8 Palms, the breadth of the Green, one Palm and two Inches; the breadth of the Narrow Red Border, eight Inches: At the top of the Staff is a Gilt Ball, and two Rings under it, for two Strings of Green Silk to run in, to keep the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard steady, and to secure it against the Wind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the Impression at the</hi> Minerva <hi>at</hi> Rome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:2"/>
            <p>A true Representation of The GRAND VISIRS STANDARD, taken at VIENNA, by the most gnvincible IOHN y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> III<seg rend="sup">•</seg> king of POLAND, And by his Maiesty sent to his Holyness INNOCENT y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true Interpretation of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Arabick words artificially Interwoven in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Standard, with an account of the Standard in Generall.</hi>
               <figure/>
               <hi>The Interpretation of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> words in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vpper part of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Standard, God hath certainly decre'd amost Glorious victory unto us, and all thy sins past &amp; to come, are graciously pardon'd by his favour. mahomet) omar) direct thee in the right way</hi> Jn the middle of the Standard, <hi>There lives no other god but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> god of mahomet Embass<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. of god there lives no other god of mahome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Embass<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. of god Jn the lower part of the Standard, Abubacher &amp; god assist thee with a powerfull hand, From them only is derived peace &amp; security into the hearts of the faithfull to the end that our faith increase in them (omar) (omar) to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> perfecting of their faith, the armyes of heaven &amp; earth belong to god.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The most Heroick and Victorius. IOHN the III<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. KING of POLAND etc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London printed for T. Malthus at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Sun in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poult F. H. Van. Houe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>Sculp</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Scanderbeg Redivivus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT OF THE LIFE &amp; ACTIONS Of the most Victorious Prince JOHN III. <hi>K. of Poland:</hi> CONTAINING An Exact and Succinct <hi>Series</hi> of <hi>Affairs</hi> from his Cradle, to this Present Day; With a particular Account of the many Great and Signa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Victories</hi> obtained by Him against the <hi>TƲRKS,</hi> from the time he was first made <hi>Crown-General,</hi> and afterward Elected King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated to the Lord <hi>Landsdowne,</hi> Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>HOLY EMPIRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. C.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Malth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Charles,</hi> Lord <hi>Lands-down</hi> (Eldest Son of the Right Honourable, the Earl of <hi>Bath,</hi> and) for his late <hi>Signal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> against the <hi>Turks,</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Count</hi> GREENVILLE of the Empire, by his <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> Majesty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Pictures</hi> of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Beauties</hi> may surprize, and be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acceptable to <hi>Strangers;</hi> but those that have the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb facs="tcp:206299:5"/>to approach a <hi>Charming Face,</hi> where <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> triumphs over <hi>Art,</hi> by displaying a thousand <hi>Graces</hi> that defie the imitation of a <hi>Pencil;</hi> will readily discover the Imperfections of a <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> and perceive how far short the <hi>Draught</hi> falls of the <hi>Original.</hi> This Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were enough to deter me from presenting your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> with these <hi>Memoirs</hi> of the most <hi>August</hi> and <hi>Heroick</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> whose Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling Virtues you have had the Happiness to view and
<pb facs="tcp:206299:5"/>contemplate <hi>near hand,</hi> and in their <hi>Direct Rays,</hi> and therefore can scarce without indignation behold them thus <hi>dully represented</hi> at distance in <hi>Broken Idea's,</hi> and as it were but by <hi>Refraction</hi> of their <hi>Illustrious Beams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Glorious Atchievments</hi> of this <hi>Mighty King</hi> are the <hi>Happiness</hi> of <hi>Our Present Age,</hi> and will be the <hi>Wonder</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> of those to come, as well as the <hi>Reproach</hi> of times past; for I must avow, I have not met with any <hi>Hero</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in History, Ancient
<pb facs="tcp:206299:6"/>or Modern (those immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately conducted by a <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Miraculous Power,</hi> excepted) whose Actions being put in Ballance, will not have reason to <hi>Blush</hi> at the <hi>Comparison.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To do him Right in a <hi>just History,</hi> will require another <hi>Livy,</hi> or a second <hi>Thuanus;</hi> in the mean time, not to be altogether wanting in those <hi>Acknowledgments</hi> which the whole <hi>Christian World owes</hi> to his Merit, I have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd this <hi>short Essay,</hi> the <hi>rude Lineaments</hi> of a most <hi>Noble
<pb facs="tcp:206299:6"/>Figure</hi> left to be perfected and polished <hi>at leisure</hi> by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Artists, the measure of some Footsteps of this <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Hercules,</hi> whereby skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Mathematicians</hi> may guess (and but <hi>guess;</hi> for they can never <hi>comprehend</hi>) the full di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensions of the <hi>Vast Body</hi> of his <hi>Worth.</hi> And I thought I could not address it to any <hi>Patronage</hi> more properly than to lay it at your <hi>Lordships</hi> Feet, who are able to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and by your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Knowledge <hi>supply</hi> the <hi>Defects</hi> of the <hi>Relation;</hi> whose
<pb facs="tcp:206299:7"/>signal Services <hi>upon the Place,</hi> and near this most <hi>Illustrious Prince,</hi> have rendred you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> by particular <hi>Marks of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> deservedly conferr'd from the <hi>Imperial Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Loyaltie</hi> are Qualities inherent in the <hi>Greenviles;</hi> Nothing could be added to that <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Stock</hi> of Renown you inherit, but by spreading it further in <hi>Regions remote▪</hi> Nor could your Lordship have an <hi>ampler Theatre</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to display your Early
<pb facs="tcp:206299:7"/>Gallantry, or a more Noble <hi>Cause</hi> to engage in, than for the common Safety of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom,</hi> at a time when so many Kingdoms and Estates did with weary Eyes, and trembling Hearts expect the Issue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> Almighty God <hi>may inspire all Christian Princes with a</hi> just <hi>and</hi> mutual Charity, <hi>to unite against the</hi> Common Enemies <hi>of our most</hi> Holy Religion, <hi>and root out</hi> Infidelity <hi>and</hi> Prophaneness, <hi>shall alwaies
<pb facs="tcp:206299:8"/>the</hi> Prayer, <hi>and that</hi> your Honour <hi>would pardon the</hi> Presumption <hi>of this</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress, <hi>is the present</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest <hi>of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships <hi>Most Humble Servant,</hi> H. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206299:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> the Second; OR, The <hi>Life</hi> of the present King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Introduction <hi>and Seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableness of the</hi> History: <hi>An Account of this Noble</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily <hi>of the</hi> Sobieski, <hi>and the</hi> Parents <hi>of this Illustrious Prince.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Stupendious Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the present King of <hi>Poland,</hi> his incomparable <hi>Valour,</hi> joyn'd with an equal <hi>Prudence</hi> of Conduct, and (through the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206299:9"/>of Providence) attended with answerable <hi>Success,</hi> has afforded Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of general <hi>Discourse</hi> and <hi>Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and the Obligations he has lately laid upon all <hi>Christendom,</hi> in repelling the barbarous incursions of the <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans,</hi> threatning, like an <hi>impetuous Torrent,</hi> to overflow <hi>Germany;</hi> after which, no <hi>Christian Kingdom or State</hi> could have promised it self security from that terrible Inundation; as it must in point of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> have exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all this part of the world to pay the iust <hi>Tribute</hi> of their <hi>Praises</hi> to his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Fame; so it cannot but have jnspir'd them with <hi>curious desires</hi> to be acquainted with the whole <hi>History</hi> of that Illustrious <hi>Hero:</hi> For who can be but impatient to know the first <hi>Bloomings</hi> of a <hi>Tree</hi> which has yielded such happy <hi>Fruit,</hi> and to the <hi>Shade</hi> of whose prosperous Arms (next the Divine Protection) they owe their Repose, To enquire after the <hi>past Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of his Life, as well as the <hi>present</hi> which have been performed on the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206299:9"/>publick Theatre; to understand the <hi>Family</hi> he derives from (since rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extraordinary <hi>Branches</hi> grow up but from eminent <hi>Roots;</hi> and <hi>Streams</hi> usually relish of the <hi>Fountain</hi> whence they proceed.) To trace the progress of his younger years, and those <hi>signal Services</hi> whereby he <hi>deserved</hi> before he <hi>wore</hi> a <hi>Crown;</hi> for <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> which in almost all other Kingdoms is (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) the designation of <hi>Nature,</hi> by <hi>Chance of Birth,</hi> is there the sole Guerdon or Reward of <hi>superlative Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> where (as of old at <hi>Rome</hi>) there is no arriving at the chief Temple of <hi>Honour,</hi> but by passing through <hi>That</hi> of the highest <hi>Vertue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Endeavour therefore shall be to gratifie such a just and becoming <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity,</hi> by Publishing the entire <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moires</hi> of this most <hi>Excellent Prince</hi> hitherto; and though I am sensible such have been his <hi>astonishing Actions,</hi> as may be apt in after-times to render whoever attempts his <hi>History,</hi> suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of <hi>Flattery</hi> or <hi>Romance</hi> (since
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206299:10"/>there want not some <hi>Scepticks,</hi> who causlesly think all the mighty Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, to be only the Fumes of <hi>Grecian Rhetorick,</hi> and worthy of no more solid Credit than the Fictions of Poets, or more modern Extravagancies of <hi>Pomish Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends</hi>) yet I am relieved against such Censures, by Publishing these <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials</hi> in the <hi>same Age</hi> wherein the Wonders therein Recorded, were Transacted, and dare appeal to all the World as <hi>Witnesses,</hi> whilst the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman Port</hi> trembles to behold her <hi>Crescent Moon</hi> forc'd by the bright <hi>Northern Star</hi> into a waning Posture; whilst the Plains of <hi>Caminick</hi> retain yet a <hi>Vermilion Die</hi> from the Blood of vanquish'd Infidels, and <hi>Vienna</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved Walls are all hung round with glorious Trophies of his <hi>Victories,</hi> it must be the highest <hi>Effrontery</hi> as well as <hi>Ingratitude</hi> for any to go about to lessen his Renown, since it cannot be done but by opposing such <hi>notorious Truths.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:206299:10"/>
               <p> This <hi>Valiant Prince</hi> is descended both by the Paternal and Maternal Line, of as ancient Noble Families as most in <hi>Poland;</hi> his Father being <hi>James Sobiesky</hi> Castellan of <hi>Cracovia,</hi> a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son no less eminent for Abilities in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of State, than for his Courage and Conduct in the Field; who was employed in the year 1621. as Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador and Plenipotentiary of that <hi>Crown</hi> upon a Treaty of Peace, which by his Prudence and Address was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily concluded upon honourable terms with the <hi>Sultan Osman;</hi> and distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guisht himself by his Merit on many other important Occasions, and after several great Services faithfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for his Countrey, exchanged this transitory Life for Immortality, in the Year of our Lord 1646.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Mother</hi> was one of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Stanislaus Zoltiewski,</hi> Grand Chancellor, and General of the Crown, who bravely fought that memorable Battel of <hi>Cicora,</hi> on the 19th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1620. And tho
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206299:11"/>he was again five times attacqu'd by the <hi>Turks</hi> on the Second of <hi>October</hi> following, yet he gallantly repuls'd them, till at last being overpower'd with Numbers, and abandon'd by his Followers, he was slain, most cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously fighting amongst the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Troops of the Infidels, on the 6th. of the same Month, and in the 73. Year of his Age.</p>
               <p>His Grand-Child, the illustrious Theme of our History, and the worlds <hi>present Wonder,</hi> was but a younger Brother, yet gave in his early Youth all the blooming Presages of a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hero;</hi> to further which, his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Parents were not wanting to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate his greener Years to the best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, allowing him an <hi>Education</hi> sutable to his <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Hopes;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he made a quick, yet <hi>solid</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress, endeavouring to surmount the Glories of his Ancestors by an acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of the most commendable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; for after he had imbib'd all the Learning which his Countrey af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206299:11"/>and was become well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Learned Languages,</hi> the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue being there almost in as frequent use as the <hi>Vulgar;</hi> he travell'd to enrich himself with Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Experience and Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and came into <hi>France</hi> with his Elder Brother <hi>Mark,</hi> who afterwards (having given most signal Testimonies of his Courage) was unfortunately slain by the <hi>Turks</hi> at the Defeat of <hi>Betow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During his Stay at <hi>Paris,</hi> he dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently applied himself to the best <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises,</hi> as frequenting the <hi>Academies, Fencing,</hi> the <hi>Menage,</hi> &amp;c. And tho then but <hi>young,</hi> did by his prudent, manly deportment, contract a great acquaintance with many persons of <hi>Prime</hi> Quality in the <hi>French Court,</hi> who regarded him with a particular Esteem: But hitherto he was only laying in a <hi>Stock</hi> of Merit and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials for a Foundation able to bear up such a vast Superstructure of <hi>Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> which in his active mind he had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206299:12"/>already designed; and therefore think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it long till he might be actually ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to his Countrey, after he had taken not a superficial view only of the fairest Parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> but through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly considered their <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests,</hi> their <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Military Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> their <hi>Strength, Defects, Polities, Obligations, Intanglements,</hi> and in a word, all that is necessary for a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Quality</hi> to observe in his <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,</hi> he hastned <hi>home;</hi> where after several <hi>Specimens</hi> of his Valour and Discretion, in quality of a <hi>Senator,</hi> he was by the then King <hi>Cassimir,</hi> made first <hi>Grand Master of the Crown, Aug.</hi> 24, 1665. and afterwards (in 1667) <hi>Grand General of the Realm,</hi> and <hi>Grand Master of the Kings Houshold, Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> of <hi>Cracovia,</hi> &amp;c, on the several oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions and Traverses of affairs herein after mentioned.</p>
               <p>But first for the Readers better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the Nature of these <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> and <hi>Preferments,</hi> and of many other Passages which we shall have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206299:12"/>on to mention in the Sequel of this Work; it will be requisite for him in general to be somewhat acquainted with the particular Constitution of the <hi>Goverumens,</hi> and past History of that Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Kingdom of</hi> Poland, <hi>and its Laws and Customs</hi> descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; <hi>with a brief</hi> Deduction <hi>of the State thereof for some Hundreds of Years past.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>POland</hi> is generally agreed to take its Name from <hi>Pole</hi> or <hi>Poln,</hi> which in the <hi>Sclavonian Language</hi> sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a <hi>Plain,</hi> or place proper for the <hi>Chase:</hi> For that the Countrey is there Composed of vast <hi>Campagn</hi> and level <hi>Woods,</hi> very fit for <hi>Hunting;</hi> but <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richovius</hi> (himself a <hi>Polander</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206299:13"/>this Derivation, and tells us 'twas first call'd <hi>Polachia,</hi> from <hi>Lachus,</hi> their first King or Leader. This Country, as it has now annext the Great Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> and other Provinces, may be numbred amongst the <hi>largest</hi> Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> extending from about the 48th. degree of <hi>Latitude,</hi> unto the 57th, and from the 38th. of <hi>Longitude,</hi> unto the 60th. making in the whole a much greater Continent than <hi>France:</hi> Being bounded on the <hi>East,</hi> for the most part by <hi>Muscovy,</hi> and in some places by the <hi>Petite Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi> Towards the <hi>South</hi> the <hi>Carpathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Mountains, and the River <hi>Neister</hi> divide it from <hi>Hungary, Transylvania,</hi> and <hi>Moldavia.</hi> On the <hi>West,</hi> it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on <hi>Germany,</hi> and touches on the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea; and on the <hi>North</hi> they have <hi>Livonia</hi> (belonging to the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi>) and part of <hi>Muscovy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Air</hi> of this Country is pure, and the <hi>Soil</hi> fruitful. The chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities are <hi>Furs, Honey, Wax, Buff-Hides,</hi> and <hi>other Skins, Masts for Ships,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:206299:13"/>and other <hi>Timber</hi> for Building, <hi>Flax, Pot-Ashes,</hi> all sorts of Grain, and <hi>Rye</hi> in abundance, whereby it hath made the City of <hi>Dantzick</hi> famous. The <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> are free, magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent, and very tenacious and jealous of their <hi>Liberties;</hi> but the <hi>Peasants</hi> or Common People are no better than <hi>Slaves;</hi> so much subjection they are in to their <hi>Lords,</hi> who treat them with the greatest Tyranny in the World; their Lives being assessed at a certain <hi>Price;</hi> and accordingly a Gentleman there values his Servants or Tenants, that is, if any of his Neighbours <hi>kill</hi> one of them, paying such a <hi>Rate,</hi> there's an end of the Business. The publick establish'd Religion is <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> tho the Light of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> darted thither its Beams from <hi>Germany;</hi> but the <hi>good Seed</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into an ill Ground, the Ignorance of the Inhabitants being very great, and no publick Care taken for regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or encouraging the <hi>Purity</hi> of Doctrine amongst them, and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:206299:14"/>being willing to <hi>connive</hi> at, if not promote <hi>extravagant Opinions;</hi> (that they the more might have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what wherewith to upbraid <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi>) several <hi>Heterodox Opinions</hi> have long since there taken footing: but above the rest <hi>Socinianism;</hi> an Instance whereof, is the <hi>Cracovian Catechism;</hi> other Books deriving their Original from thence: Their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is a Dialect of the <hi>Sclavonian;</hi> but most of them do also speak <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Government, 'tis the <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Kingdom or Royalty (under which Term I intend not to include the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi>) that is at this day <hi>Elective</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> for tho the Crown of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> were generally so for many Ages, till in the Year 1660. the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of that Kingdom were made (or forc'd) to alter it, yet now his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of <hi>Denmark</hi> writes himself He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as well as of <hi>Nerway.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:206299:14"/>
               <p>'Tis commonly believ'd, that the first People (of whom we have any Records left) entring <hi>Poland,</hi> were the <hi>Huns</hi> and <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> whom, <hi>Orichorius</hi> says, came from about <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi> and yet retain in their vulgar Tongue some relish of the <hi>Greek Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage;</hi> and that they having driven thence the <hi>Suevi</hi> and <hi>Goths,</hi> and other People who were possest of all that Tract of Land from the River <hi>Vistula,</hi> even to the <hi>Elb;</hi> at last one <hi>Lechus,</hi> (or rather <hi>Lachus</hi>) made himself their Chief, about the Year of our Lord 350, and commenced the Monarchy of <hi>Poland;</hi> from whom there are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned 14 Princes to <hi>Miesko</hi> (or <hi>Micis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi>) who began his Dominion, <hi>Anno</hi> 964. and was the first <hi>Christian</hi> Duke of that Country, being Baptized up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Marriage with a Daughter of <hi>Boleslas</hi> Duke of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the 7th. of <hi>March,</hi> 965.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Micislas,</hi> his Son, Named <hi>Boleslas,</hi> succeeded in the Year 999. and was by the Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> the 3d.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206299:15"/>(going to visit the Tomb of St. <hi>Adel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> whom those of <hi>Prussia</hi> had slain) Created <hi>King.</hi> After whom came <hi>Micislas</hi> the Second, Father of <hi>Casi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir</hi> the First; followed by his Son <hi>Boleslas</hi> the Second, Sirnamed <hi>The Cruel;</hi> for that he put to Death <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nislaus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Cracovia;</hi> for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment whereof, <hi>Poland</hi> lost the Title of a <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and was govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by several Princes or Regents, till it again recovered the Quality of a <hi>Realm</hi> under King <hi>Primislaus,</hi> about the Year 1295. To whom succeeded <hi>Ladislas</hi> the Third; who after four years was expelled; and <hi>Vinceslas,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> chosen in his room; but after five years <hi>Ladislas</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>established; and next came <hi>Casimir</hi> the Third, called <hi>The Great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After whom, <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> being chosen King of <hi>Poland,</hi> left two Daughters; the younger of which, being declared <hi>Queen,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wirh <hi>Jagellon</hi> Great Duke of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania,</hi> who, upon these Espousals,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206299:15"/>being Baptized (for before he was a Pagan) was accepted for <hi>King,</hi> and his Countreys were united to the Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> about the Year 1386. He at his Christning taking the Name of <hi>Ladislas;</hi> who had for his Successors <hi>Ladislas</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Ladislas</hi> the Fifth, King of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>Casimir</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>John Albertus,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Sigis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> the first and second: Which last dying without Children, in the Year 1572. the <hi>Polanders</hi> chose <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> (second Son of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second of <hi>France</hi>) who was Crowned <hi>Febr.</hi> 15, 1574. But that Prince being advised of the Death of his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. quitted his <hi>Elective</hi> Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> to take up that of <hi>France,</hi> falling to him by Inheritance, in the Year 1576.</p>
               <p>After whose Recess, the <hi>Poles</hi> not agreeing in their Election, one Party named <hi>Stephen Batheri,</hi> Prince of <hi>Transilvania;</hi> and the other <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206299:16"/>Arch-Duke</hi> of <hi>Austria;</hi> which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion'd a War between them, But the <hi>First</hi> carried it, and died without Issue, 1586.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Sigismund</hi> (the <hi>Third</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> of that Name) Son of <hi>John,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> was chosen to the Throne; soon after which, his Father dying, he was also Crowned King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> but having been secretly bred by his Mother (who was a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist</hi>) in her Religion (unknown to his Father, who was a zealous <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi>) and he having upon his <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the Diadem of <hi>Poland,</hi> made publick Profession of the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion,</hi> the States of <hi>Sweden,</hi> upon their Receiving and Crowning him King, oblig'd him to <hi>Conditions</hi> of maintaining their then received Religion (which was as still it is, the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Perswasion) and that he should no way endeavour the introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of <hi>Popery;</hi> which <hi>Articles</hi> he soon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206299:16"/>after violating, by erecting, or suffering <hi>Popish Churches,</hi> and placing <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to be <hi>Governors</hi> of Castles, Forts, and Places of Importance and Trust, whereby they perceived his Resolutions to bring in upon them <hi>that Religion;</hi> they <hi>revolted,</hi> and accusing him of <hi>Breach of Faith,</hi> &amp;c. proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>depose</hi> him, and set up his <hi>Ʋnkle Charles</hi> (the Third Son of his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father <hi>Gustavus Errickson</hi>) in his stead.</p>
               <p>Hence arose the Foundation of <hi>Fewds</hi> and <hi>Wars</hi> between <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden; Sigismund</hi> prosecuting his Claim and Pretensions, and <hi>Charles</hi> justifying his <hi>Election;</hi> which Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel descended to their Posterity; for <hi>Sigismund</hi> dying in the Year 1632. <hi>Ladislaus</hi> his Eldest Son followed; who also departing this Life in 1648. his Brother <hi>Casimir</hi> was chosen, who Reigned Twenty Years, and then (as we shall shew more at large in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206299:17"/>following Pages) voluntarily surren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dring the Crown, <hi>Michael Corib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Wiesnowiski</hi> was chosen King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and he dying in 1673. this <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sobietski</hi> by his Merits, and those ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Services he had rendre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Countrey, was unanimously E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thought it not unnecessary to give this short Deduction, since it may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much serve to illustrate after-Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages; as also it will be convenient to acquaint the Reader, That the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> being thus <hi>Elective,</hi> are very much <hi>restrained</hi> and <hi>limited</hi> in their Power; some <hi>Authors</hi> telling us, That the King takes an Oath not only to <hi>Govern according to the Laws, Statutes and Customs of the Kingdom,</hi> to <hi>maintain the Rights and Priviledges of every Order,</hi> and <hi>not to diminish the Revenues of the Realm;</hi> but also that there is a Clause in his Oath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to the <hi>Absolving</hi> of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206299:17"/>from their <hi>Obedience</hi> in case he Rule otherwise: But as the latter seems strange, and yet is no more than what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n effect is contained in the <hi>Aurea Bulla,</hi> or Fundamental Law of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> in relation to the Emperor, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore may probably be true; yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the form of the old Oath of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olish</hi> Kings, Publish'd by <hi>Orichovius,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do not find any mention of it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, this is on all hands agreed, That by the ancient Constitution, Laws and Customs of that Kingdom, the King can do nothing considerable without the consent of the Estates; and that he must in making Peace or War, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of Taxes, alienating Lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Crown, or ought else of importance to the Commonwealth, have the advice and concurrence of the <hi>Senate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the <hi>Nobles</hi> have such an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the Supream Government, so subordinately they assume (or have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206299:18"/>formerly done it) a greater pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than they allow to their <hi>King</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> self; for in their several and respectiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Seigniories,</hi> they behave themselves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>absolute Lords;</hi> the Realm being d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Thirty four <hi>Palatinates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Governments;</hi> each of which has u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him <hi>Castelains,</hi> that is to say, <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> or <hi>Governors</hi> of Cities; of who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there are in <hi>Poland</hi> in all about t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> number of 87.</p>
               <p>As for their Grand <hi>Ecclesiastick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> they have two <hi>Archbishops, viz.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Gnesna</hi> and <hi>Leopold</hi> (there was fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> merly another at <hi>Riga,</hi> till that Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fell under the <hi>Swede.</hi>) The <hi>Arch-B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> of <hi>Gnesna</hi> is the prime Senator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> State, and upon the Death of a King he hath the chief Management of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> and issues out Precepts for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Election of a <hi>new</hi> Prince, and adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters the <hi>Oaths</hi> to him when he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chosen.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:206299:18"/>
               <p> Their most important <hi>Affairs</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>solved on and determined in <hi>Diets</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Parliaments held after this manner; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he King by his <hi>Chancellor</hi> sends to the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>relates</hi> and <hi>Palatines</hi> his Letters call'd <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>structionis Literae</hi> [Letters of Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion] which mention the Matters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at his Majesty will propose to the Assembly, and appoints the <hi>Time</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Meeting; which Letters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng received, each of the Senators <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onsiders in particular the Nature, the Quality, and the Consequences of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hose things, touching which he has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iberty to give his <hi>Vote</hi> as he pleases, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither in reference to the Publick Good, or his Private Interest.</p>
               <p>But besides this, the King also sends his Letters into every <hi>Palatinate,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them when the Nobless is to assemble; and willing them to chuse one or more <hi>Representatives</hi> of their <hi>Province,</hi> whom they called <hi>Land-Nuntio's;</hi> and for this purpose,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206299:19"/>they have a Convention held in each County, call'd <hi>The Landt-Jag,</hi> si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> weeks before the Session of the <hi>Diet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at which a Commissioner from the King is present, who declares wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to be debated in the ensuing Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his Majesties part: Upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which they deliberate, and then chuse Members for their several Provinces, giving them <hi>their Instructions</hi> (which they must exactly follow) in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Kings Desires, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a Liberty to propound what they shall find conducible to the Good o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Countrey.</p>
               <p>Now this distinct Body of <hi>Nuntio's</hi> tho less in dignity than the Senate, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> equal to them in Authority, is a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance to the Senators, controuling o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, if from the Bounty or Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the King, they should prove corrupted or byass'd to the endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their <hi>Liberties.</hi> And therefore they generally chuse the most prudent and sufficient Persons to that Trust;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206299:19"/>and indeed they had need be wise; for such is their Constitution, That if in the <hi>Diet,</hi> upon any Debate, there shall happen but <hi>one single Gentleman</hi> (be he <hi>Senator</hi> or <hi>Nuntio</hi>) to dissent, and obstinately persist therein, nothing can be Concluded by all the rest on that Point; and therefore all their Determinations are made with an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Suffrage, or (as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly express it) <hi>Nemine reclamante.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Besides the <hi>Palatinates,</hi> the Cities of <hi>Cracow, Dantzick</hi> and <hi>Vilna,</hi> have the priviledge to send their <hi>Deputies</hi> to the <hi>Diet,</hi> who have Seats in the <hi>Chamber of the Nobles:</hi> But ordinary <hi>Affairs</hi> are heard and dispatch'd by <hi>Judges</hi> establish'd in each <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the <hi>Burgraves</hi> of each City, where it is permitted to all sorts of Persons to be present; as also in their <hi>Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Assemblies;</hi> so that the <hi>meanest Peasant</hi> may, if he please, know all. The King's <hi>Chief Revenue</hi> arises from <hi>Salt-pits,</hi> and the <hi>Mines</hi> of <hi>Copper</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206299:20"/>
                  <hi>Lead,</hi> and in some places <hi>Silver.</hi> He has the Nomination of <hi>Prelates,</hi> and all <hi>Dignities of the Realm,</hi> and the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of War,</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Justice,</hi> and of <hi>Policy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Highest Honours are these; of the Grand Marshal of the Crown, Grand Master of the King's Houshold, the Grand Chancellor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:206299:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Marriage of</hi> Sobiesky, <hi>and his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to the Charges of</hi> Grand Marshal, <hi>and</hi> General of the Crown; <hi>wherein occasionally is given a Brief Account of the Reign of King</hi> Casi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir, <hi>and the manner of his Resign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crown.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THough the great <hi>Sobiesky</hi> began early to devote his Services to <hi>Mars,</hi> yet he escaped not the sweet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anglements of <hi>Cupid; Love</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sually intermix the Stories of <hi>Heroes:</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or as <hi>Valour</hi> is the Property of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated Souls, and a constant Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant of the most Generous Breasts, so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re they the most susceptible of the <hi>Noblest Passions:</hi> Nor is it to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eckoned amongst the least of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood Fortunes, That in his Youth he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206299:21"/>made so brave a Conquest as the Heart of Madam <hi>Arquiem,</hi> one of the most Considerable Ladies in the <hi>Polish Court,</hi> both for Quality, Beauty, and Fortune; 'twas the Charming Idaea o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his brave Person and Vertues made the first Impressions on her Soul, and she had not been wanting to testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on several Occasions, that his Addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses were not displeasing to her, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rather gave him sufficient grounds to promise himself the Happiness of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Favour.</p>
               <p>But she being one of the Queen Ladies of Honour, Her Majesty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed her for a Match to the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Zomoski</hi> (one of the greatest Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of that Kingdom) and in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> absence of <hi>Sobieski</hi> prevailed so fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the Lady, being then very young and asham'd to own her pre-engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that she was Married to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince: But he Living not long, sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being then at Liberty to pursue he own Inclinations, was shortly after Espoused to <hi>Sobieski,</hi> bringing him a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206299:21"/>
                  <hi>Beauty</hi> more advanced, together with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he accession of a vast <hi>Dowry</hi> added <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o her proper Fortunes; by which Alliance Heaven has blest him with <hi>several Children,</hi> and particularly <hi>Prince Alexander,</hi> of whom we shall have occasion anon to speak further, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he having already <hi>Signaliz'd</hi> himself, and shewn the World that he resolves to follow the steps of his Gallant Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor indeed can any but a Prince of his promising Merit be fit to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and advance that <hi>Mighty Glory</hi> to which he is Apparent Heir.</p>
               <p>The 24th. of <hi>August,</hi> 1665. <hi>Castmir,</hi> then King of <hi>Poland,</hi> thought fit to give <hi>Sobieski</hi> the Office of Grand Marshal of the Crown, in the room of <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> then discharged of that Office for his Rebellion in Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Party called <hi>The Confederates,</hi> which was like to have destroyed the <hi>Polish</hi> Kingdom; and concerning the Original of which it will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit here to give a brief Account.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:206299:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Casimir</hi> being Elected <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. to the Crown, did, by a Dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Pope, Marry the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict of his <hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>Predecessor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dislaus,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Lady, and of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enterprizing Temper, whose after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intermedlings in Affairs of State, and Endeavours to promote a <hi>French</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor, is thought to have much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Disturbances and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of that Kingdom: But its first Calamities arose from an Invasion made by <hi>Charles Gustavus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> about the Year 1655. To which he was disposed, partly by his <hi>Martial</hi> Temper, and that <hi>Feud</hi> that had long been between them, by reason of the Kings of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions to the Crown of <hi>Sweden;</hi> and partly, as excited by <hi>Ragieski,</hi> late Vice-Chancellor of <hi>Poland,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Married a Young and very Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Lady, the King, who was Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Amorous, Courted her, and they long had an Intrigue together, till <hi>Ragieski</hi> at last perceiving it, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:206299:22"/>away his Wife from Court to a <hi>Countrey-House</hi> at a distance: The King incensed to be thus deprived of his <hi>Mistress,</hi> Commands him back to Court, under pretence to render His Majesty the Services which the Duty of his Office required: But soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he was Accused of Caballing against the Interests of the State, and holding Intelligence with the Enemies of the Crown; and notwithstanding all the Opposition of the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Gnesna,</hi> Primate of the Realm, in his Favour, Condemned to lose his <hi>Place,</hi> Forfeit his <hi>Goods,</hi> and be for ever <hi>Banish'd.</hi> The Parents and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of this Noble-man Murmured aloud at this procedure, and many others stuck not to say, that the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Priviledges, and Honour of the <hi>whole Nobility</hi> were violated in his Person, and so became dis-affected towards the King, whilst <hi>Ragieski</hi> himself taking shelter in <hi>Sweden,</hi> knew he could no way better ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate there, than by discovering the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206299:23"/>Weaknesses of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents that were amongst its Gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees.</p>
               <p>All which made such Impression on the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing there was a <hi>Truce</hi> depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he entred <hi>Poland</hi> with a Formi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dable Army, and like a <hi>Whirlwin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> he forc'd his Passage, took the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Cities, <hi>Warsaw</hi> and <hi>Cracow,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over-run the whole Kingdom, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Palatines and Chief Lord espousing his Party, so that King <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simir</hi> was forc'd to fly to the Border almost generally deserted, only th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> City of <hi>Dantzick</hi> persisted in u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> movable <hi>Loyalty;</hi> and to their Fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lity next under God, <hi>Casimir</hi> owe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Recovery of his Kingdom an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Crown. For <hi>Charles</hi> being not ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to win that City, and his Souldier committing all kind of Spoils an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cruelties, the <hi>Poles</hi> began to forsak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him and return to their Duty. Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Casimir</hi> gathered up an Army able to make Head against the Enemy, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:206299:23"/>having worsted them in several Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, and the <hi>Dane</hi> at the same time falling upon the <hi>Swedish</hi> Territories at home, that King was fain to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge his Conquests as fast as he had gain'd them, and <hi>Casimir</hi> was quickly not only Re-establish'd in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, but to chastise the <hi>Great Czar,</hi> who had Assisted the <hi>Swede,</hi> carried the War successfully and with mighty Devastations into <hi>Muscovy,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged them to an Advantagious Peace.</p>
               <p>Affairs being brought to this Happy Calm, the King having no Issue, nor like to have any, the Queen-being a passionate Advancer of the <hi>French</hi> Interest, as being her Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, moved the King to procure a <hi>Successor</hi> Nominated in his Life time, and strongly Endeavoured that the Duke <hi>D'Enguien,</hi> only Son of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> might be the Man, and Marry her Neice, the Daughter of the Princess Pallatine: Nor were the <hi>French</hi> Pistols wanting to dispose
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:206299:24"/>the Court-party to that Choice. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> extreamly irritated others of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nobles to oppose such a Design amongst whom <hi>Lubomirski</hi> was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chief, with whom a strong Part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> joyn'd, that called themselves <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Confederates:</hi> But after several Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verses of War, and Treaties betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, he was put to the worst; hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Place of Grand Marshal taken from him, and he forced to Retreat to <hi>Breslaw</hi> in <hi>Silesia,</hi> where he afterward dyed of a <hi>Palsie</hi> in <hi>Jan.</hi> 1666/7.</p>
               <p>In the mean time his Office o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grand Marshal was (as you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard) confer'd upon <hi>Sobieski,</hi> and soon after the Crown-General <hi>Potos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> departing this Life, that <hi>Importan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Charge</hi> was also committed unto him though many opposed it, alledging that it was not fit two such great <hi>Trusts,</hi> as <hi>Marshal</hi> and <hi>General</hi> should both be managed by one Person, and therefore would have had the same enjoy'd by Prince <hi>Demetrius,</hi> a Prince of great Interest and Merit. But indeed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:206299:24"/>the Exigencies of <hi>Poland</hi> at that time required no less than the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Valour of <hi>Sobieski</hi> to Relieve them; For the <hi>Cossacks</hi> (who are a People composed of many Strangers of several Nations, but the Gross of them consists of <hi>Polish Peasants,</hi> who to avoid the Servitude of the Nobles, have abandoned their Countrey, and withdrawn themselves into the <hi>Ʋkrain,</hi> a Province bordering on the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> plentifully abounding with all things necessary for Humane Life; where they follow the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, as to Religion, and have a <hi>Patriarch</hi> of their own, Residing at the strong and great City of <hi>Kioff:</hi> They acknowledge themselves gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Subjects to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and serve him in repelling the Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of the <hi>Infidels</hi> without any Pay, being always in Arms for their own Security, but their Resentment is so violent against the <hi>Nobles,</hi> and the ill will of the latter so great against them, to reduce them to an intire Vassalage,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:206299:25"/>that they are frequently in Arms on against the other.) These <hi>Cossacks,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> say, having now joyn'd with the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> and promised Assistance from the <hi>Turks,</hi> Invaded the Frontiers with great Spoils, taking the Town o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Podhays,</hi> and blockt up <hi>Russe-Lemberg</hi> against whom General <hi>Sobieski</hi> advan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing about <hi>Sept.</hi> 1667. was by reason of their numbers reduced to grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> streights, they having surrounded him with their Army, but Animating hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Men by his Exemplary Courage, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> issued out upon them with a great slaughter of the Enemy, and little loss on his side; and so not only quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himself of those disadvantages but brought them to conclude a Treaty on the Terms following. First as to the <hi>Tartars:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1. That there should be an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty</hi> for all things done in the late War, till the Signing of the Treaty.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That if any <hi>Differences</hi> should for the future arise, they should not presently return to Arms, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:206299:25"/>to Reconcile them by their <hi>Envoys.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Sultan Gilga,</hi> in the Name of the <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary</hi> his Master, Engaged himself to be an Enemy to all such as should make War upon the <hi>Poles,</hi> and to Assist them with Forces when-ever required, for which the <hi>Poles</hi> were to pay them a Yearly <hi>Penston,</hi> and for so doing to give <hi>Hostages,</hi> until the States (which were to be Assembled about <hi>January</hi> following) should have raised Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for their present satisfaction.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Cham</hi> should not Quarter any of his Forces in <hi>Ʋkra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> or any other part of the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Dominions without his consent.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That if any of the Foreign Forces which had been in the Army of the <hi>Cham</hi> should make any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursions into <hi>Poland,</hi> he should nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give them Assistance nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:206299:26"/> 6. That Prisoners on both side should be Released; and that Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan <hi>Galga</hi>'s Forces should comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no Disorders in their Return.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The Treaty with <hi>Doroskensko,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the <hi>Cossacks,</hi> was thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1. That they should have a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Pardon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That they should seek no other <hi>Protection</hi> than from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that the <hi>Pole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> that live amongst them may quietly enjoy their Estates, as the <hi>Cossack</hi> should what they possess'd in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Army of <hi>Zaporanisk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> may send their Deputies to the States of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that none of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Forces should be sent into any of their Cities and Towns.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Governour of <hi>Biala-Cieurky</hi> should be Ordered not to disturb the <hi>Cossacks.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>'Tis most true, that the <hi>Grand Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal</hi> had done abundance of Illustrious <hi>Actions,</hi> which render him worthy of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:206299:26"/>that <hi>Figure</hi> he has since made in the World, but it must be avowed, that this was so eminent, as it might <hi>alone</hi> have entituled him to the Reversion of that Crown, which he now enjoys with so much Glory: For in that Juncture, considering with what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and fore-sight he prevented such a pressing Danger, and the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of these <hi>Treaties,</hi> wherein the Honour of the King was conserv'd, and the Realm set at <hi>Peace,</hi> nothing could be more seasonable, or worthy of Praise.</p>
               <p>But still the <hi>General</hi> well knowing that the <hi>Tartars</hi> are a People that use not to be very much slaves to their words, and that without doubt they had some amongst them, which in their March homewards, would Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abroad to Plunder, put himself in the Head of a Party of Horse to observe their Motions, and finding a Detachment of them near <hi>Jarnipolis</hi> beginning to Pillage, came suddenly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:206299:27"/>upon them, slew divers, and force the rest to fly to their Main Body.</p>
               <p>The General <hi>Diet</hi> met not till <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 24. at <hi>Cracow,</hi> where the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Succession</hi> being taken into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the States publish'd a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance of the following purport.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That whereas all the <hi>Difference</hi> and Troubles which have lately arise in this Kingdom, have sprung from no other cause than the Electio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (which some Persons intended t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have made) of a <hi>Successor</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Crown during the Life of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent King: For the timely preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so great an Inconvenience. We by these Presents, Declare to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> World our dissatisfaction in that point, and that in case of an <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum,</hi> should His Majesty (to whom we wish a long and happy Life) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this World, We have Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted and Agreed amongst ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> selves to resume and observe all and every point of the Order made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Elections;</hi> as also the <hi>Diploma</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:206299:27"/>of <hi>Sigismund</hi> the Third, and in no wise to allow of or consent to any such Election during His Majesties Life, but to hold and Esteem all and every Person that shall be found to Oppose the same, as Enemies to our Countrey. And if any Ministers of Foreign Potentates shall endeavour to advance their own Interest by Encouraging any such Election, We shall declare and proceed against them (notwithstanding the Law of Nations) as <hi>Enemies</hi> of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. And whensoever His Majesty shall depart this Life, we shall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Obligation, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon the News thereof, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Election</hi> of a <hi>New King,</hi> without expecting an <hi>Ʋniversal Diet.</hi> Further declaring, that whoever shall forcibly endeavour to obtain the Crown, shall be proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst as a common Enemy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the matter of Chusing a <hi>Successor</hi> was laid aside, and during these Disputes, the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:206299:28"/>dyed, which together with the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents of that ill-regulated Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the perpetual Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moils he was in, induced the King to an irrevocable Resolution to <hi>Resign</hi> the Crown, and betake himself to the <hi>Solace</hi> of a private Life. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, at a Convention of the Senators, <hi>June</hi> 12. 1668. He by his Chancellor gave in to them the following Paper.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>It is not unknown to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, That it hath been long since the intention of His Majesty, even during the Life of his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort the <hi>Queen,</hi> of Glorious Memory, but especially since Her Majesties De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease, to Resign the Government of the Kingdom. To put this Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into due effect, His Majesty hath only expected a convenient Season and good Opportunity, having been forced upon the account of the late <hi>Confederation,</hi> the Wars with the <hi>Muscovites</hi> abroad, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions at home, to defer the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof until now. For as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:206299:28"/>much as it was to be feared, that during these Disturbances and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>settlements, the Republick might be highly endangered by an <hi>Inter-Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> But now, since by the Divine Goodness, Peace appears again at home, and a Truce is concluded with the <hi>Muscovite,</hi> His Majesty is fully Resolved with all convenient speed to execute his said Intention; to which he is induced upon sundry private Considerations, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by his great Indisposition of Body, which disables him any longer to support the Burthen of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: His own Conscience also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring some interval of Retirement between the Cares of Government and the end of his Life. But above all, having especial regard to the Publick Peace and Prosperity, since His Majesty finds, that to break the Malice of those Men, who by mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>representing his good Intentions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually perplex the Republick with the Jealousies of a forcible Election,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:206299:29"/>he cannot but by his own demissie give them this certain mark of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Royal Affection by leaving them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> an intire exercise of a Free Choice.</p>
                  <p>For these Reasons His Majesty after Mature Deliberation, Declare That he will Resign the Crown in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the hands of the Republick, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out Reflecting on the Counsels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> your Lordships and the several F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign dissuasions from this Resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For His Majesty hath not no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Assembled your Lordships to as your Advice whether he should R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign or not, since he means not all to submit his firm and irrevoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Resolution to any Arbitramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nor to hearken to any Considerat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Intreaties that can be offere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the contrary, but only that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> might Advise with you about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Manner and Solemnity of his R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation, that so this Work may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> done with most Advantage for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> safety of the Republick, the sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Peace during the <hi>Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:206299:29"/>Regnum,</hi> and the greatest Freedom in the future Election.</p>
                  <p>And to the intent His Majesty may perform what is requisite on his part for the fore-mentioned Ends, to put to shame those Malicious Persons, whose Tongues have given out, as if he had already transacted with a Foreign Prince: He is so far inclined to concur with the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for a Free Election, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires not so much as to Recommend to them any one of the Candidates; and to the end his presence may not administer the least Umbrage of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbing their Freedom, His Majesty is Resolved, during the Election, to remove from <hi>Warsaw.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor will His Majesty be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to the Republick upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his own future Interest, assuring himself, That the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in their approaching Election, will cause to be inserted the Articles of Capitulation, That the succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Regent shall take due care for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:206299:30"/>a fixed Maintenance of him after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Resignation.</p>
                  <p>And this is that which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty was willing to propose to you Lordships Consideration, That yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would agree on such away of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation as might be safe to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, to himself Honourabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and expedient for the Republick Declaring, That he intends to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed thereunto in the next Die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which he much desires may be A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled the first of <hi>August,</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> end, that the Solemnities of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Inter-Regnum</hi> and the Election ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be ended before the next Winter.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Pursuant to this Resolution, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 16th. of <hi>September</hi> following, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Estates being Assembled in the Cast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Warsaw,</hi> King <hi>Casimir</hi> made t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them the following Speech.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:206299:30"/>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>YOu see at last that moment wherein your King and your Father, to consummate that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with those of his Family, for more than two hundred years past, have had for your publick Weal, finding himself too weak to support at once both the burthen of <hi>Age,</hi> and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <hi>Affairs,</hi> comes to remit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> our hands the <hi>Crown,</hi> that most precious and desirable thing amongst Mortals. Behold, I say, the time which is the <hi>Funerals</hi> of my <hi>Glory:</hi> For henceforth I am <hi>Dead</hi> to the World, and shall rather chuse instead of a <hi>Royal Globe,</hi> a small <hi>Turf</hi> of Earth, wherein, with the Benevolence of the Republique, I may repose amongst the <hi>Ashes</hi> of my Predecessours, That it may be read in your <hi>Annals,</hi> That I whom you have so often seen in the head of your <hi>Armies,</hi> and alwaies the <hi>last</hi> in a Retreat, am also the <hi>first</hi> that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:206299:31"/>voluntarily deprived my self of tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> human Grandeurs, and surrendred t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> you the <hi>Royal power,</hi> from a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> tender Love towards my Countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Your kindness and the free Suffrage of those present at my Election, raise me to this high degree of Majesty and my reciprocal affection induc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> me to despoil my self thereof in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> grateful requital. My <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>esto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>'s,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> have been your <hi>Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>en by n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> cessity of nature, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ave quitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> the Diadem, have left either Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or some of their Blood, who Relation and Vertues have oblige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> you to consider them in the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Election. But I for a Testimony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> my affection to the Publique, gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> up <hi>all</hi> I have received, and leave entirely to whomsoever is <hi>better ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> to serve you. It has been my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> fortune to fall into such unhapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> times, that the Soveraign Dignit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> wherewith you invested me, has no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> only contributed innumerable <hi>Tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> to my self (which for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="47" facs="tcp:206299:31"/>sakes I should have endeavoured to struggle with) but given causes of <hi>Jealousies</hi> to others; I desire pardon for what has been done amiss during the time of my Reign; and that you would impute my Errors to Humane frailty, and wish my <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor</hi> may prove more Fortunate both to his own Concernments and those of the Republick.</p>
                           <p>And that you may be Happy in your Choice, I shall in my Solitude beseech God to Illuminate you with his Blessing on this occasion, and at present return you all the Thanks I can possibly, for the Love you have shewn me, for the good <hi>Offices</hi> I have received of you, the <hi>Counsels</hi> which you have given, and the <hi>Aids</hi> and Supplies you have so liberally offered me. And thus with all the Endearments imaginable, It ake leave of you, hoping that you will not fail to conserve me in your Memory. 'Tis with these Sentiments that I give you all a <hi>Fatherly Benediction,</hi> assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:206299:32"/>you, that if I shall happen to be at never so far a distance in Body from my <hi>Dearest Countrey,</hi> I shall be always entirely united thereunto in Mind and all the Affections of my Soul, and hear with an extream Joy <hi>that Kingdom</hi> to flourish and be it Repose by anothers <hi>Conduct,</hi> which under me has more than once bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> at the very brink of Destruction—I would say more, but am hindred through want of <hi>Memory,</hi> and that tenderness of my Heart, which suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers me not to speak further to you but with my <hi>Tears.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This Pathetick Speech ended (which set all the Assembly a weeping) King <hi>Casimir</hi> Publickly Resigned the <hi>Crown, Scepter,</hi> and other Ensigns of Royalty, and departed in the Quality of a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Nobleman: However the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral our Generous <hi>Sobieski,</hi> with all the Nobles waited on him to his Apartment, and the <hi>States</hi> in grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude soon after presented him with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:206299:32"/>his Assurance of an Honourable Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enance for his Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>WE the States Ecclesiastical and Civil, as also Inhabitants of the two Nations of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Lyffland</hi> in Council Assembled, do by these Presents Certifie and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish to all the World and to our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, That we have humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought, and by all ways imaginable endeavoured to perswade <hi>John Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simir</hi> our King and Master, that he would not Relinquish that Crown, to which himself, as formerly his Ancestors, the Renowned and Mighty Kings of <hi>Poland,</hi> had been Elected, but that he would continue the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment so long as he lived. But for as much as no persuasions could induce His Majesty to alter his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution, but that he hath freely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed the Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> and great Dutchy of <hi>Lyffland,</hi> together with all their Dependencies into the Hands and free disposal of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:206299:33"/>we knowing not how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> resist His Majesties Intentions herein His Majesty desired that we would make some convenient Provision fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his future subsistence; which being a point in which we had not receiv'd the Advice of our Brethren in their Provincial Assemblies, we were ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> willing, out of our Affection to Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Majesty, to agree and consent to the Allowance of an Yearly Pension of 150000 Livres, whereof this Kingdom to be Charged with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Payment of One Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, and the great Dutchy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Lyffland</hi> with Fifty Thousand, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Revenues of the Kings Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: The said Sums to be fixt and specified at the next Election. And that the Lords of the Treasury of both Nations, not attending the said specification, shall make an Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the said Pension from the day of His Majesties Resignation. And this we do promise to get con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in our Provincial Assemblies,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:206299:33"/>and to make Provision for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity thereof by an Agreement with the succeeding King. Further Agreeing, That this Allowance both from this Kingdom and the Dutchy of <hi>Lyffland,</hi> shall continue during the Life of His Majesty, and to be paid fully and wholly to him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Abatements, Fees, or Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications whatsoever.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:206299:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Election of Prince</hi> Micha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Koribut Wiesnowiski <hi>to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Crown of</hi> Poland, <hi>and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Eminent Services of</hi> Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sobieski <hi>during his Reign.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>KING <hi>Casimir</hi> having thus aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the Government, <hi>Sep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 16th. 1668. The Arch-Bishop o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Cnesna</hi> (according to his Office) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed himself to take care of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> State during the <hi>Inter-Regnum,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appointed a General Assembly for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> New Election to be held at <hi>Warsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>May</hi> following.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the several <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates</hi> were busie in making the Parties: As the Son of the Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:206299:34"/>Duke of <hi>Muscovy</hi> (who had been bred in <hi>Poland,</hi> and spoke that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) on whose behalf the Duke his Father offered, that he should <hi>Change</hi> his Religion, and embrace that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, make a Renunciation to <hi>Muscovy,</hi> That all places formerly taken from <hi>Poland</hi> should be restored. That four Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions should be Advanced as his Free Gift for the Payment of the Arrears of the <hi>Polish</hi> Army, And that he would be Obliged to Assist <hi>Poland</hi> against all Enemies whatsoever with an Army of 40000 Men, and enter into a firm and perpetual League with them. The next was the Duke of <hi>Neuburgh,</hi> a Brother to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> whom the Emperour seemed much to favour in his Pretensions. A Third was the Prince of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and a Fourth the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s Son, whom the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Gnesna</hi> and General <hi>Sobieski</hi> were thought to Favour.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:206299:35"/>
               <p> Towards the beginning of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1669. the Grandees began to Reso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Warsaw,</hi> in Order to the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Election. On the first of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Duke <hi>Michael Radzevil,</hi> General o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Field in <hi>Lythuania,</hi> made his Entr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a stately Equipage: First, Marche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> five Companies of <hi>Heyduques,</hi> consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an hundred in each, with their Ensigns flying, and Drums beating, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> clad in large blew Vests lined with Yellow: Then a Foot Company o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sixty in Yellow clad like <hi>Janizaries</hi> followed by two Troops of Dragoon well Mounted, with blew Coats and Silver Lace; then a Troop of <hi>German</hi> Horse in excellent Accoutrements, followed by as many <hi>Hussars,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them by 60 Gentlemen of Quality Richly Habited, with their Lances after the <hi>Turkish</hi> Fashion; Then came Duke <hi>Radzevil</hi> himself, followed by above 200 of the Lords and Principal Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Lythuania,</hi> all splendidly Array'd, and their Horses extraordinarily Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed, and among them divers of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:206299:35"/>most Ancient Nobility, as Prince <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vislaus Lubomirski,</hi> the Lord <hi>Potoski.</hi> These were followed at some distance by a great number of Gentlemen their Attendants, with their other Servants in Rich Liveries, after whom marched two Troops of <hi>Tartarian</hi> Horse, an hundred in each Troop, followed by five Troops of Dragoons in blew Coats with Silver Lace: And lastly, a full Company of <hi>Heyduques</hi> brought up the Rear.</p>
               <p>This Entry, though Magnificent, was much exceeded in the Afternoon by that of the Lords <hi>Pazzi,</hi> the one Great Chancellor, the other Great General of <hi>Lythuania,</hi> who had thrice their Number and Attendance.</p>
               <p>But all these were Eclipsed by the more Illustrious appearance, <hi>May</hi> 3d. of General <hi>Sobieski;</hi> all the Princes and Nobles doing him the Honour to meet him some Miles from the City, who was followed by a vast number of Gentlemen and Officers, and had a stately Company of <hi>Janizaries</hi> (like
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:206299:36"/>those of the <hi>Grand Signior</hi>) for his Guard in most sumptuous Habit. The <hi>Waywood</hi> of <hi>Cracovia</hi> also came At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a Train of above 5000 Persons.</p>
               <p>The Diet being begun, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles having Elected the Lord <hi>Potoski,</hi> Brother-in-Law to Prince <hi>Slavislaus Lubomirski,</hi> for their Marshal or Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, an Oath was proposed to, and taken by the Senators and Equestrian Order, in these terms.</p>
               <p>I <hi>Swear, That I neither already am, nor hereafter will be bound or engaged either by Word or Writing, to any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner or stranger in the Election of a Prince. That I neither already have, nor will enter into any Party or Faction, nor suffer my self to be corrupted through Gifts or Rewards by any Foreign Princes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I will not give my Vote or Suffrage for any Person but such as I shall judge fittest for the Administration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Kingdom. And if I have formerly obliged my self to any
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:206299:36"/>Foreign Prince, I do hereby Renounce the said Obligation, and leave his Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, the Diet establish'd a <hi>Chamber</hi> or Court of Justice, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of Senators and several <hi>Waywoods,</hi> selected Persons of the respective Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, who were to take care of all Affairs concerning the Crown, and to prevent Disorders which daily hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by such a vast concourse: And of this Court, <hi>Marshal Sobieski</hi> was appointed President.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Dutchess of <hi>Muscovy</hi> happening to dye, that Duke was so Afflicted therewith, that he had some thoughts of committing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to his Son, and so gave over his Sollicitations for the Crown of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> so that now there were only left three Parties, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Neuburgh,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> each en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to exclude the other. But soon after, the nomination of the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was excluded by the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:206299:37"/>Diet, and the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Gnesn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was openly called <hi>Traitor,</hi> and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be <hi>Killed</hi> for offering to but speak in favour of the <hi>French</hi> Interest; and some Menaces were made by the Nobles to <hi>Sobieski</hi> on that Account, he being suspected a favourer of that Party, by reason of his Alliance with a <hi>French</hi> Lady, <hi>Mary de la Grange,</hi> Daughter of the Marq. of <hi>Arquiem,</hi> and Widdow of Prince <hi>Zomoski,</hi> as before mentioned.</p>
               <p>Then the Competition between the Duke of <hi>Neuburgh</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was bandied very obstinately, so that it was much feared it might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion a Rupture, and the contending Parties fall to blows: To prevent which, on the 19th. of <hi>June,</hi> the Lord <hi>Opalinski,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Calitz,</hi> made an Eloquent Harangue between both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherein having at large demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated the <hi>fatal consequences</hi> of such <hi>Heats,</hi> he began to Expostulate with them how they came to be so passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately concerned for two Princes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:206299:37"/>whom they were strangers unto, and either of which, for ought they knew, might treat them ill, when once he had got Possession of the Crown, and therefore he Advised them rather wholly to lay aside those Foreign pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions, and chuse a <hi>Piasti,</hi> that is, some Nobleman of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, of whose Vertues and Temper they had Experience; and for his part, he knew none of greater worth, or better deserving the Royal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, than Prince <hi>Michael Koribut Wiesnowiski,</hi> which Nomination was presently received with general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, the Assembly crying out, <hi>Vivat! Vivat!</hi> And the said Prince being then present, was immediately forced by the Assembly to be <hi>Covered</hi> and <hi>Take a Chair,</hi> which he refused, urging his Incapacity to support so Weighty a Crown; but the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly not hearkning to his Apology, Obliged him, not without Tears in his Eyes, to accept the Honour: All the rest of the Provinces and Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinates
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:206299:38"/>giving in their <hi>Suffrages</hi> to his Choice, save only the Grand Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Patz,</hi> the Principal Person of <hi>Lythuania,</hi> who affirmed he would not give his Voice for any but the Prince of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> But his Brother, the Palatine of <hi>Troski,</hi> shewed him the Inconveniences of refusing a <hi>Piasti,</hi> encouraging him to Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate one of his own side of the Countrey; whereupon he named Prince <hi>Boguslaus Radzevil,</hi> for whom there appeared a considerable Party, but that of <hi>Wiesnowiski</hi> upon the Competition prevailed, and in the Heat <hi>Killed</hi> two Gentlemen upon the place, who spake over-boldly against their Choice.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:206299:38"/>
               <p> Things being thus carried, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal <hi>Sobieski,</hi> and the Marshal of the Nobless, retiring themselves, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested</hi> against the Election, but the prevailing Party slighted it; and demanded of the Archbishop of <hi>Guesna</hi> to <hi>proclaim</hi> the Election, but he pretending some Indispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would have delayed it, till they threatning to oblige the Bishop of <hi>Cajari,</hi> and he supply that Office, he then appeared in the Field, with the two Marshals, and according to Custom demanded three times, <hi>That if they were agreed upon the Election, they should name the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> which they did with great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, accompanied with the discharge of all the Cannon; this being about eight a clock in the Evening, and before nine, the King was Proclaimed, and so Conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Castle, and next day in St. <hi>Johns</hi> Church took his Oaths he Observ'd, the <hi>Pacta Conventa,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:206299:39"/>or Agreements concluded upon; then dined with the Primate, and afterwards went into the Field of <hi>Kolu</hi> (the place where the Election was held, some distance from the City) and returned his thanks to the several Waywodeships, Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, and Provinces.</p>
               <p>Both the Archbishop of <hi>Gnesna,</hi> and Marshal <hi>Sobieski</hi> were dissatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Irregularity of this Election, yet for the publick quiet, complyed therewith. And when shortly after some stirs were like to happen in the <hi>Army,</hi> upon a report that he was to be turned out of his Command as General, he being sent down thither, not only paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them in that, but other their discontents, and retain'd them in their due Obedience to the Crown, and in <hi>January</hi> following the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars of <hi>Dialogrod</hi> falling into the <hi>Ʋkrain</hi> and <hi>Podolia,</hi> where they made great spoil, and had taken
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:206299:39"/>a multitude of poor people Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, he advanced against them, and put them to flight, leaving the most part of their Booty, and Prisoners behind them.</p>
               <p>The 27th of <hi>February,</hi> 1669/70 King <hi>Michael</hi> was Married to <hi>Eleanor,</hi> the Emperors Sister, by reason of which <hi>Alliance</hi> Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies were raised, that His Majesty had a mind to make himself <hi>Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi> and <hi>Hereditary,</hi> and subvert the <hi>Polish</hi> Liberties. Insomuch, that at a Diet or Assembly of Estates held soon after, the <hi>Equestri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Order put up several Requests, and amongst others, that the <hi>Pacta Conventa,</hi> or Agreement concluded upon, when he was chosen King, might be openly read; their other desires his Majesty readily Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but was loth to grant this, till finding them resolv'd not to proceed in any business, till that were granted, he condescended
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:206299:40"/>thereunto, and accordingly next day the <hi>Equestrian</hi> Order went to the House of Senators, where His Majesty was seated under a Canopy of State, and the Senators on each side of him, and there the said <hi>Pacta</hi> were publickly read, at the last Article whereof, which impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>That if the King did not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and duly perform his part, what he had there promised, then they were discharged from their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to him;</hi> They all gave a loud shout. [Which passage serves to reconcile the <hi>difference</hi> of Authors touching that Kings <hi>Oath,</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d. for though there are no such <hi>express</hi> words in the Terms of the Oath, yet it seems they are wont to be contained in the <hi>Pacta Conventa,</hi> which by that Oath he swears to observe.]</p>
               <p>The Kings Uncle, Prince <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius Wiesnowiski,</hi> was Lieutenant General under <hi>Sobieski,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:206299:40"/>them two, there was no very good Correspondence; to bring them to a better understanding of each other, the King used several means, and to Crown the work, it was resolved, that the said Prince should <hi>marry</hi> with the Princess of <hi>Ostrogy,</hi> Sister to the Prince of that Name, and <hi>Neice</hi> to General <hi>Sobies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ki;</hi> which was performed with great Solemnity, and thencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Animosities between these two great men ceased.</p>
               <p>In the year 1672. The <hi>Cossacks</hi> assisted by some <hi>Tartars,</hi> having again faln to their old habit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and General <hi>Sobieski</hi> with the Forces of the Crown, having Chastised them for the same, and forced their Leader <hi>Doreskensko</hi> to retire; the <hi>Turk</hi> took thence an occasion to quarrel with <hi>Poland,</hi> upon pretence that he had taken the <hi>Cossacks</hi> into <hi>his protection;</hi> and making a sudden inroad, besie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:206299:41"/>the City <hi>Camieniec,</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made their Approaches under the shelter of great Sacks filled with Cotton Wool, and raised a Battery, upon which they planted 12 whole Cannons, with which for 12 whole days they continually plaid most furiously upon the Town; the Besieged were forced to surrender upon Articles, to march out with Bag and Baggage, the whole Garrison not being above 500 men, of whom 200 were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately killed by the accidental blowing up of a Tower by their own Powder; the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> was personally present at the taking of it, and entred the Town the same day it was yielded, and placed therein a Garrison of 8000 <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> his whole Army consisting of near 190 thousand Horse and Poot, as was reported.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> was at this time at <hi>Jauowitz,</hi> expecting the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:206299:41"/>Arrival of the Nobility, who were from all parts resorting to him; and to gain time, he sent Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> to treat of a Peace, or procure a Cessati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whereupon the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> return'd him this Answer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the Vice-Chancellor of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE Letter of the most Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene and Honourable King of</hi> Poland, <hi>our Great Friend, to our most Serene, most Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and most Potent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the World, and Monarch, like to</hi> Alexander <hi>the Great, who is the Shield of the whole World, was together with your Letter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to me, brought to my hands in our Camp near</hi> Caminiec, <hi>some days before our taking of that place; I delivered the Imperial Letter to His Majesty, and having caused
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:206299:42"/>mine to be Translated, I understood what you wrote. That which I did write to you from</hi> Adrianople, <hi>gave you notice of what hath since hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and may serve for Answer to these Letters; But you were want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do those things in time, which were necessary for the Preservation of your Country; and therefore have seen and heard things which you would not, and what is to follow, is known to God alone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We always wrote both to your King and you, what hath now come to pass, which you might have prevented by sending Ambassadors to his Imperial Majesty, with Royal Presents, as is usual, and promise of Tribute, who thereby might have appeased the burning wrath of our Great Lord, and obtained better Conditions for you; nay, had you ever since (for the Gate of Mercy of our Emperor is open to all) sent Ambassadours to offer a Tribute, it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:206299:42"/>was to be hoped they might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the good will of our Lord, and he permitted them to renew the ancient Peace and Friendship. If therefore after all, you have any care for the quiet and good estate of your Armies, Kingdom and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, do what you intend very sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, without any delay, and the sooner you do it, the more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious it will be for you. That you have desired the most Glorious</hi> Cham <hi>of</hi> Tartary <hi>to be Mediator at this Treaty, you do well, for he hath offered his friendly persuasions on your behalf. Peace be to those that believe the Commandments of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>But the Winter coming on apace, and sharp weather, hindred the <hi>Turks</hi> further Advance, and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Sobieski</hi> falling unexpectedly upon a Body of 20 thousand <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> (at that time Consederates with the <hi>Turks</hi>) at a place called <hi>Try,</hi> totally routed them, killing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:206299:43"/>10000 of them, as also rescu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very near as many poor Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whom they were carrying away into miserable slavery; and soon after defeated another Party of them with great slaughter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Country was freed from their Rapine and Devastations, which was generally acknowledged to be a most acceptable and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious service to the Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> at that juncture.</p>
               <p>The King having summoned the <hi>Arrier Ban</hi> (that is, a General Convention of all the <hi>Nobless</hi> throughout his Dominions) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in their Arms, lay Encamped near <hi>Samosch,</hi> where amongst other things, the Nobility took into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideration the Party called <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents,</hi> amongst whom they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Bishop of Guesna,</hi> the <hi>Crown Ensign,</hi> and many others, and ordered that they should be <hi>summoned</hi> to appear and take <hi>an
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:206299:43"/>Oath of Confederation,</hi> which was there framed, and upon their taking the same, a general <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> to pass; but if they should refuse to appear and enter into the same, then they were to be declared Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, their Offices disposed of to others, and all their Goods and Estates to be Confiscated. Which Oath ran in these words.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I.</hi> N. N. <hi>Of my own free Will, and without any Constraint, do swear by the Holy and Blessed</hi> Trinity, <hi>that for the Honour of God, the Dignity and Welfare of our Free Elected and Crowned</hi> King and Lord, <hi>and the preservation of this Republick, and the Priviledges and Liberties thereof, against all Enemies whatsoever, I will readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expose my Life and Fortunes; and that I will not forsake or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from this Confederation, till our Country be freed from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:206299:44"/>of any Enemies as well</hi> at Home <hi>as abroad, but will do all that shall lie in my power for the making this Treaty more strong and valid, until we shall have obtained the ends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and if I come to know that any Person does Act in prejudice of this Confederation and Brotherly Agreement. I shall be obliged to discover the same, without having the least respect to</hi> Friendship <hi>or</hi> Relation, <hi>and account and prosecute him as an open Enemy. I have not taken any</hi> Money <hi>to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor will I take any. I will not hold any</hi> Intelligence, <hi>or Act on any occasion to the prejudice of my King and Country, but will truly and sincerely observe this Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Brotherly Ʋnity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mental Reservation, or hope to be dispensed therefrom. So help me God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Things running thus high, seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:206299:44"/>of those accounted <hi>disaffected,</hi> retired to <hi>Meaco</hi> in <hi>Prussia;</hi> but the Archbishop of <hi>Guesna</hi> remain'd at <hi>Lovitz,</hi> his usual Residence, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming not at all concern'd at the heats of the Nobless, who offered 1000. <hi>Ducats</hi> to any that should bring his Head into the Leaguer, and threatned to proceed to <hi>Depose</hi> or degrade him; but <hi>that</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> opposed, as being a viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ecclesiastical Liberty, for that <hi>Lay</hi> Assembly to proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a <hi>Churchman</hi> without leave from his Holiness.</p>
               <p>In the mean time Commissioners sent by the King to the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi> clapt up a Peace with the Port on the following Articles.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the</hi> Tarrars <hi>formerly In habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kingdom of</hi> Pol. <hi>called</hi> Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cees, <hi>and who have since quitted their abodes there, and given themselves up to the protection
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:206299:45"/>of the Port, yet so as to leave their Wives and Children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, shall have free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to return and fetch away their said Wives and Children, and their Goods and Moveables whatever, and that such as shall desire still to abide in</hi> Poland, <hi>shall have liberty so to do, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any molestation or distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That the King of</hi> Poland <hi>shall by his Ambassadours send yearly to the Port</hi> 22000 <hi>Ducats, which shall be paid every year on St.</hi> Demetrius-day, <hi>being the</hi> 15th <hi>of</hi> Novemb. <hi>on this Condition, that the</hi> Grand Seignior <hi>shall secure the Subjects of the Crown of</hi> Poland, <hi>against the incursions of the</hi> Turks, Tartars, <hi>and other people subject to the Port; and in case the</hi> Poles <hi>shall at any time be endammaged by them, the King of</hi> Poland <hi>shall demand
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:206299:45"/>satisfaction of the</hi> Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, <hi>and forbear to pay the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovementioned Tribute, till he shall have received it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Podolia, <hi>as in ancient time shall be subject to the Port; and in case any difference shall arise con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Limits, it shall be amicably decided by Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be to that purpose deputed by both Parties.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The Garrisons which the</hi> Poles <hi>now have in any place or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tress in</hi> Podolia, <hi>shall immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately be drawn out from thence, and have liberty to return home with their Goods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>On the other side, the</hi> Grand Seignior <hi>shall restore all places taken from the</hi> Poles <hi>in</hi> Russia.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Free Exercise of Religion shall be granted to all Persons.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Such as desire to depart with their Goods and Families out of</hi> Caminiec, <hi>shall have free liberty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:206299:46"/>so to do, and return into</hi> Poland <hi>within the space of two months, after the Ratifying of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>The</hi> Ukrain <hi>shall be left free to the</hi> Cossacks <hi>as in former times, and the</hi> Poles <hi>shall quit all the Forts and places they have pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd themselves of there, and shall depart with all their Goods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>except their Cannon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>The</hi> Cossacks <hi>that have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Hanensko, <hi>may return to their former Habitations in the</hi> Ukrain, <hi>if they shall think fit, and no injury shall be done them by the other</hi> Cossacks; <hi>but</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensko <hi>himself shall remain in</hi> Poland.</item>
                  <item>Lastly, <hi>All former Treaties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> Poland <hi>and the Port, shall remain in force.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Besides all which, there was a separate Article that the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> should pay a Tribute of 16
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:206299:46"/>thousand Ducats to the <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Agreement, so prejudicial and dishonourable to the <hi>Poles,</hi> as rendring that Crown Tributary to two of its Infidel Neighbours, at a time when it might have been in a condition to defend it self, (for besides the Army, with the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> the King at <hi>Lublin,</hi> had above 100000 men in Arms) was very ill resented by General <hi>Sobieski,</hi> and many others, who lookt upon it only as a <hi>Politick Device,</hi> that in the mean time the <hi>opposite Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> might be at leisure, and have opportunity to crush those they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Malecontents;</hi> and therefore though two <hi>Senators</hi> were sent from the Convention to the Army, to invite them to enter into the aforesaid Oath of Association, yet he declined it.</p>
               <p>The Peace being thus concluded with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the Polish No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility finding themselves unable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:206299:47"/>longer to subsist in the Field, by reason of the ill weather, and for want of Forrage and Provision, did about the latter end of <hi>October</hi> break up their Assembly; only left a party of 2300 men in Arms for the Kings Guard, and agreed that a General Assembly of the Deputies of the several Palatinates should be held in the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> and there the <hi>Confederation</hi> begun in the Leaguer to be confirmed, and then to proceed to the Tryal and Condemnation of such of the <hi>Malecontents</hi> as should continue to absent themselves, and refuse the before recited <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the Army entred into a Counter-Confederation, wherein they declare, <hi>They will defend the Liberty of their Country, and the Priviledges of the Nobles,</hi> which (they alledg'd) <hi>under pretence of adhering to the Royal Authority were violated, and endeavour'd to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:206299:47"/>be suppress'd; and that therefore they were resolved to protect those of the Nobility, which were so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely prosecuted under the name of</hi> Malecontents, <hi>and disturbers of the Peace of the Kingdom, Titles which much more fitly belong'd to their Accusers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pursuant to this Declaration, the Army began to Advance somewhat towards <hi>Warsaw,</hi> which put the Court into great Consternation, but General <hi>Sobieski</hi> thought fit not to approach further than <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witz,</hi> being willing to determine all differences by an amicable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posure; and accordingly after se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Overtures, towards the end of <hi>March</hi> 73, an Accommodation was made upon the Terms following,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That all past Offences should be forgiven and forgotten.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>That the Confederation made the last year by the Nobility.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:206299:48"/>should be Cancel'd and made void.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>That all those, who had during these unhappy misunderstandings been Branded by the name of</hi> Malecontents, <hi>should on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, without exception or distinction partake of the Kings favours, with, and as well as, the rest of the Nobility.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>To confirm this good Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the Grand-General <hi>Sobieski</hi> came to <hi>Warsaw</hi> with a numerous Train, where he was complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the part of the King by the Vice Chancellor, and by the <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode</hi> of <hi>Posen</hi> for the Senate; and in the name of the Nobility Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the <hi>Diet</hi> by two of their Deputies, and by the said <hi>Diet</hi> it was ordered that he should be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented with 50 <hi>thousand Dollars,</hi> as an acknowledgment of his good Services; but he generously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the present necessities of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:206299:48"/>the Publick, freely abated one third part thereof.</p>
               <p>In Council he vigorously urg'd the regaining of that Honour, which by an unhappy Treaty had been lost the last Summer, and that it might never be said the <hi>free Crown</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> had for a day been <hi>Tributary</hi> to the Sworn Enemies of <hi>Christendom,</hi> opposed the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any of the Mony agreed on; offering that With an Army of 60 thousand (if the <hi>State</hi> would take care for their pay) he did not doubt but to give a good account of this Summers Campaign; which much encouraged the <hi>Diet</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve upon and prepare for a War, and in order thereunto, the <hi>Crown-Jewels,</hi> which they had before ordered to be Pawned, valued at 600 thousand Livres, were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted in his hands for securing the Army their Arrears; and so forthwith his Excellency departed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:206299:49"/>to <hi>Sokal,</hi> where the Army was Rendevouz'd, extreamly satisfied with his Conduct.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Archbishop of <hi>Guesna</hi> departed this life, <hi>April</hi> the 12th, 1673. and in his Room the King advanc'd the Bishop of <hi>Cujavia</hi> to succeed him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding these resolutions and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in <hi>Poland,</hi> dispatcht thither the following Letter (though not delivered by the <hi>Chiaux</hi> till after the Kings death.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THou the chief Prince of the Christian People, Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the</hi> Nazarene <hi>Kingdom of</hi> Poland, <hi>King</hi> Michael <hi>our Friend, may your Administration have an happy Issue. By these Letters We give you to understand that</hi> Achmet Bassa, <hi>our</hi> Grand Vizier, <hi>is the chief Administrator of our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Dignity and Authority of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:206299:49"/>whose Ministry let God encrease: We have not long since understood, that you refuse to pay our most Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Majesty the</hi> Tribute <hi>stipulated by the late Treaty between us and you; and to remove the Garrisons out of your places on the Frontiers; wherefore it appears clearer than the</hi> light, <hi>that you have broke the</hi> Peace <hi>that was concluded with me; &amp; is it thus lawful for you in so short a time to violate the Peace? The Governors and Souldiers of our Frontier places have not done your Subjects any damage, nor given you any cause of Offence, wherefore then have you broke the Peace? And why have you provoked Me the Monarch of the World to Anger? What? Do your Souldiers think to delude us? Send us quickly the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and the Gifts, which by vertue of the Treaty (tho by you violated) and the promise of your Envoy, ought to have been paid on the day
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:206299:50"/>of St.</hi> Demetrius <hi>last past. Send them quickly if you will, that the ancient Treaties between us be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served and re established: Send the Gifts, restore the Castles, repair the damages, and do it sufficiently, unless you desire to be by my Arms compelled to it. If you omit it, by the help of God, I will with innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Armies infest and destroy thy</hi> Poland. <hi>Be therefore ready for War, and send back my Messengers quickly, that I may know thy mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But these proud <hi>Menaces</hi> were in vain, the <hi>Invincible Sobieski</hi> had advanc'd to the banks of the River <hi>Niester,</hi> and by a Commanded Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty sent out under the Conduct of the Crown Standard bearer, taken in the strong Town and Castle of <hi>Miedzibos,</hi> after an obstinate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance; as also <hi>Jaslowiec,</hi> and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other places, and brought off great numbers of Prisoners, from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:206299:50"/>whom he understood, that the <hi>Hussam Bassa</hi> lay on the other side the <hi>Niester</hi> with a Body of 40000 men, expecting a great Reinforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come up to him out of <hi>Asia,</hi> whereupon he resolv'd with all expedition to pass the River, and give them Battel, before the arrival of those Troops.</p>
               <p>Accordingly having pass'd over the Army, he advanced towards the <hi>Turks,</hi> who lay commodiously entrench'd under the Walls of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thim,</hi> greatly exceeding the <hi>Poles</hi> in number; and his Cavalry being on the 9th of <hi>Nov.</hi> 73. come within Cannon shot of their Leaguer, the Grand Marshal went in Person within Musket snot of the Enemies Camp, to observe in what posture they lay, and at his return call'd a Council of War, where it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd, that considering the want of Provisions, under which the <hi>Polish</hi> Army at present labour'd, it was
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:206299:51"/>their best course to Attack the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels <hi>in their Trenches.</hi> Towards Evening his Foot and Train of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery came up, several little skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishes having in the mean time pass'd between his foremost Troops, and those of the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The next morning, <hi>Nov.</hi> 10. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Sobieski</hi> drew up the whole Army into Battalia, and having placed his Artillery (which consisted of 50 pieces of Cannon) most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently for annoying the Enemy, advanced in good Order, and with great resolution towards their Camp; and being come pretty near it, the <hi>Hospodars</hi> of <hi>Wallachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia</hi> (Provinces formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Poles</hi>) revolted from the <hi>Turks,</hi> and came over to the <hi>Polish</hi> Army with 5000 men, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately all things were ordered for the Attack; which was to be made in five several places, the <hi>Crown Watchmaster</hi> was posted
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:206299:51"/>next the <hi>Neister,</hi> on the side of <hi>Czeczora,</hi> next him the General <hi>Sobieski,</hi> and then the under Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Wisnowiski,</hi> assisted by the <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode</hi> of <hi>Kiovia,</hi> the other two were to be manag'd by the Troops of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania;</hi> in which order they had beset the Enemy, but because re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the Army into this posture took up much time, that night the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were not wanting in their defence, seemed to have some advantage over them; Collonel <hi>Danemark</hi> a brave Commander in the <hi>Crown-Watchmasters</hi> Quarter, and Captain <hi>Jarozki,</hi> with many other Officers and common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being cut off; the Enemies loss was altogether as great.</p>
               <p>That whole night the <hi>Polish</hi> Troops stood ready in Arms with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Musket shot of the Enemies Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment, and early next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Nov.</hi> 11. General <hi>Sobieski</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured again <hi>on foot</hi> to discover
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:206299:52"/>the posture they were in, and the many of his Officers would have dissuaded from so hazardous an Attempt, continued in his Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to fall upon them. And now he ordered his Cannon to play ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furiously on the Enemy, and having every where given the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Orders, encouraged his Troops with assurance of Victory, telling them, they fought not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>Honour,</hi> but also for the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of their Countrey, and (what was yet infinitely more valuable) their <hi>Religion;</hi> and so marched with his drawn <hi>Sable</hi> in his hand <hi>on foot</hi> at the head of them till they came up to the Tutks En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, and then mounted on Horseback, the like being done by the rest of the great Officers. The first discharge was of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, who in the space of a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Masters of the Enemies Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:206299:52"/>and made great slaughter amongst them; upon which the foremost of the Infantry, who should have seconded the Horse in pressing on upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, thinking they had already won the Battel, began to fall to <hi>Plundering,</hi> which the <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse perceiving, sell upon them, and did great Execution amongst them; and would have done much more, had not the <hi>Hussars</hi> come in to their assistance, who again put the Enemy into disorder, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Hussain Bassa</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Turkish Army, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself unable any longer to stand the Shock, began to retreat with many thousands of his Men towards <hi>Czraozo,</hi> but the <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode</hi> of <hi>Bleski</hi> and the Sicur <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouwski</hi> observing it, Intercepted his passage, and forced him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back into the Battel, where General <hi>Sobieski</hi> with a party
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:206299:53"/>Rencountred him, but being much inferior in number, and the <hi>Turks</hi> fighting (like their condition de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperately) tho the General himself performed wonders as well by the slaughters he made with his own Hands, as by the encouragement his Example and Words gave to his followers, yet things were like to have fallen into much confusion, had not the <hi>Hussars</hi> once more come in with incredible Resolution, and then the Battle seemed altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as fierce as when it first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; so bravely did they behave themselves on both sides, but after a long and bloody dispute, the <hi>Crescent</hi> gave way to the <hi>Cross,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> were broken to pieces, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many thousands of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions dead on the place; so that the Field was covered with breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less bodies, and of those that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to escape the greatest part were drowned in the <hi>Neister;</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:206299:53"/>so that of their whole Army which according to the modestest Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation consisted of between 30 and 40 thousand Men, there were not 5000 that escaped; and as there was no Quarters given du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the heat of the fight, so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently there were very few Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners; amongst the dead were found <hi>Heybegh Bassa,</hi> and <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Bassa</hi> two great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but their General <hi>Hussain</hi> had the luck to make his escape, and fled to <hi>Caminiec.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>Poles</hi> side the loss was considerable, the General Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master, the Crown-Hunter, the Lord <hi>Starosta Wolbramski;</hi> the Lord <hi>Rzeozky,</hi> the Lord <hi>Rozmia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowski,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Hussaws,</hi> and many other Officers slain; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides those that were wounded.</p>
               <p>After the fight ended the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had leave to Ransack the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Leaguer, where they found
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:206299:54"/>great Booty, and to compleat the Victory, the next day they took the Castle of <hi>Cothim</hi> by <hi>Storm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The joyful news of this Grand Victory (chiefly owing to the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conduct of General <hi>Sobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eski</hi>) found <hi>Poland</hi> in Mourning; for in the very time that the same was gaining, King <hi>Michael</hi> after some weeks lingering Indisposition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life at <hi>Lemburgh Nov.</hi> 10, 1673. whence his Corps was removed to <hi>Warsaw,</hi> where being Embalmed, it was (according to custom) to remain unburied, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till after the Election of a new King.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:206299:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>General</hi> Sobieski <hi>Elected King; His sudden Conquest of the</hi> Ukra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 1674. <hi>with</hi> 4000 <hi>Men he Routs</hi> 60000 Tartars <hi>near</hi> Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pold, August 75. <hi>and in</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember <hi>following with</hi> 15000 <hi>chases before him above</hi> 100 <hi>thousand of the Enemy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>'TIS hard to imagin, much more to <hi>express</hi> what unusu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al transports the <hi>Polish</hi> Nation felt upon the Arrival of these two <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> Tidings; <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> like contrary Torrents, struggled in their Breasts, ready to overwhelm them with a <hi>Neutral Astonishment.</hi> The death of their King in the <hi>Flower</hi> of his Age (for he was but in his 33th. year) leaving the Kingdom not only engaged in a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:206299:55"/>terrible War abroad, but (what was worse) <hi>Embroil'd</hi> and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being torn to pieces by Factions at home, and the Clashing Interests of <hi>Pretenders</hi> to the Crown, was matter of an afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Consideration: But on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, such a <hi>Glorious Victory</hi> just in the nick, seem'd a good <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of future success, and that the Divine Favour designed not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon the State of <hi>Poland</hi> to the Malice and Cruelties of its Enemies, since it had so signally appeared for its preservation: And besides the present security, this prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Battel brought to their Affairs (<hi>Hali Bassa</hi> who was advancing with a numerous Host to reinforce, <hi>Hussain Bassa</hi> having upon the News of his total defeat, Retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the <hi>Danube;</hi>) The terror it struck into the Enemy, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement it gave the <hi>Polish</hi> Soldiery, the influence it had on
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:206299:55"/>Revolted Provinces, and Waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friends, all vastly augmented the Import of it; for Kingdoms and States as well as Merchants, subsist as much by <hi>Reputation</hi> as by real Intrinsick strength; an instance whereof was soon found here, for immediately on this Blow to the <hi>Turks,</hi> the Envoy from the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muscovy,</hi> offered <hi>Poland</hi> in the Name of his Master an Assistance of 50 thousand Men against them, tho he very little observed this promise afterwards.</p>
               <p>Nor was <hi>Sobieski</hi> wanting in the part of a discreet General, to <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> this Victory, but presently dispatcht some Troops under the Command of the Crown-standard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer into <hi>Walachia,</hi> the better to secure that Countrey in their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and sent other Forces under the <hi>Weywode</hi> of <hi>Braklaw</hi> to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter round about <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and so strictly Blockade that place, that no
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:206299:56"/>provisions might be brought into it; after which, having disposed the rest of his Troops in fit Winter Quarters, he came to <hi>Lemburgh</hi> resolving to reside there all the Winter to be near at hand in any emergency; nor could the Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Nobles,</hi> nor of the Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> her self, who wrote to him to be present at the <hi>Diet</hi> at <hi>Warsaw</hi> in <hi>January,</hi> about the <hi>Election,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him; so much did he prefer the service and safety of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey before the pursuing and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing his own Interests.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>January</hi> the 15th. 1673/4, the <hi>Diet</hi> met for the first time, and chose the Lord <hi>Bielmiski</hi> to be their Marshal, or Speaker; the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Nobility seemed inclinable to make choice of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son qualified to <hi>Marry</hi> with the Queen <hi>Dowager,</hi> as well for their Affection to her Majesty, as in <hi>Good Husbandry</hi> for the Publique,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:206299:56"/>to prevent the many Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that might accompany a New Queen, especially in point of Charge, when instead of <hi>one</hi> they must provide Dowries for <hi>two.</hi> Amongst the Candidates, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> seemed to stand fairest, for besides the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the Emperour and the Queen <hi>Dowager,</hi> engaged in his favour, many of the Noblest greatly esteemed his person for the vigour of his <hi>Youth,</hi> and the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience he had already had of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Affairs; whilst those that opposed him, had only to alledge, that 'twas to be feared he would be too much addicted to the House of <hi>Austria.</hi> But all that this <hi>Diet</hi> agreed on considerable, was to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the <hi>time</hi> of Election to be the 20th. of <hi>April</hi> following.</p>
               <p>At which day they Reassembled accordingly, and began to adjust the Preliminaries, but General <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bieski</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:206299:57"/>arrived not at <hi>Warsaw</hi> till the 2d of <hi>May,</hi> making his entry then with great Solemnity; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides <hi>his Guard</hi> of two Troops of Horse, and a Regiment of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and his <hi>Train</hi> which were numerous of persons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, most of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators</hi> that were there went forth to meet him, at the Pallace of Prince <hi>Radzevil</hi> Under Chancellor of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> he alighted and was with all his Retinue entertain'd at a Noble Banquet: The next day his Excellency went out of Town to pay his Respects to the Queen, and on the fourth of <hi>May</hi> was the first time he appeared in the <hi>Diet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where for several days following, there happen'd a long and brisk Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test between the Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of <hi>Poland,</hi> and those of the Dutchy of <hi>Lithuania;</hi> the former proposing him the said <hi>General So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bieski</hi> to the <hi>Publick Choice</hi> as a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:206299:57"/>person eminently deserving of the Republick by the continued services he had rendred it, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the <hi>Victory</hi> obtained in the last Campaign over the <hi>Turks</hi> at <hi>Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> which next to the Divine Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance they solely attributed to his great Courage and Conduct; and that at present being engaged in a War with so powerful an Enemy, they thought they could not make choice of <hi>any</hi> one, whose Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in Military Affairs, and his other great Abilities could render more meriting the Crown than he: Adding, That a <hi>Forreign Choice</hi> would but engage them in Forreign Interests, which might perhaps be more regarded than the welfare of the Crown. The <hi>Lithuaners</hi> on the other side, urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the general Resolution of the Nobility of that Dutchy, not to admit of any <hi>Piasti</hi> (that is, a Native either of <hi>Poland</hi> or <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania</hi>)
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:206299:58"/>for that they had found the ill consequences of it, during the late Kings Reign by the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> some of the Nobility had stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up against him; and therefore they ought to chuse a Forreigner, and such a Prince, who besides his other endowments rendring him worthy of the <hi>Crown,</hi> could be a fit <hi>Husband</hi> for the Queen <hi>Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and who was assisted by pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful <hi>Alliances,</hi> the better to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the republick to carry on the present War against the <hi>Turks;</hi> on all which Considerations they knew none fitter to be their King than the Prince of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> Some there were that nominated the Prince of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> but their number was not considerable; but after all these Disputes, General <hi>Sobieski</hi> was by plurality of Votes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at last almost unanimously E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected King on the 21st. of <hi>May</hi> 1674. with the great Applause
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:206299:58"/>of the People of that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>And accordingly the Bishop of <hi>Cracow</hi> in the absence of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Guesna</hi> (who was sick) did with the usual solemnities pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly declare him King by the name of <hi>John the third King of</hi> Poland, <hi>Great Duke of</hi> Lithuania, &amp;c. Who forthwith was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously pleased to promise of his own free will and motion, That the <hi>Queen Dowager</hi> should be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for according to her high Quality, and extraordinary Merit; as also, that the <hi>Arrears</hi> of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my should be forthwith discharged out of his <hi>own</hi> Revenues, seeing the Publick could hardly do it at present. He also expressed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self willing to Confer the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Grand Marshal, or General, on Prince <hi>Demetrius Wies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowiski,</hi> Uncle to the late King, and that of Lieutenant General of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:206299:59"/>the Crown (thereby becoming va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant) to the <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Kiovia,</hi> but as he signified his Resolution to prosecute the War against the <hi>Turks</hi> with the utmost vigour, or oblige them to an Honourable Peace, and to that purpose that he would at his <hi>own particular charge</hi> raise 1000 Foot, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them during the War, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the <hi>Senators</hi> and other Great Men of the Kingdom to do the like proportionably; so he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired that he might retain the command of <hi>General</hi> in his own hands till <hi>this Campaign</hi> be ended, for that the present urgent Affairs of the Kingdom were like to prevent his <hi>Coronation</hi> before the Campaign; which the Nobility assented to: As likewise that the Article offered in the <hi>Pacta Conventa</hi> obliging the King not to Resign the Crown on any occasion whatsoever, should be omitted.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:206299:59"/>
               <p> The 15th. of <hi>May died</hi> the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Guesna</hi> scarce warm in his place, and the King raised the Bishop of <hi>Culm,</hi> a Person of great esteem and merit, to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in that dignity. The Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> by the consent of the King and <hi>Diet</hi> had a yearly Revenue of 200 thousand Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Assigned her, with liberty to reside in any place within the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Territories, except <hi>Cracow,</hi> or some other fortified places on the Borders of <hi>Silesia;</hi> and her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty made choice of <hi>Thorne</hi> in <hi>Prussia</hi> for her Residence.</p>
               <p>Tho his Majesty was most soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous for carrying on the War, yet the Nobility and Senators w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e generally as <hi>Remiss</hi> therein, for tho they had promised him at first maintainance for 60 thousand Men, he now desired it but for 40000, and yet such were their Dissenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Jealousies as would not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:206299:60"/>permit them to consent thereunto.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the <hi>Muscovites</hi> pretending Friendship with the <hi>Poles,</hi> and that they would oppose the common Enemy, had on the contrary only fallen upon <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roskensko,</hi> Head of the Rebel <hi>Cos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacks</hi> and recovered many places in the <hi>Ʋkrain</hi> to inlarge their Territories that way; However the <hi>Great Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary,</hi> and the Grand Seignior with their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hastned thither to oppose the <hi>Muscovites,</hi> and in short time had over-run another great part of that Countrey; so that the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince was like to be intirely lost. wherefore to give what Assistance he could in such an unfortunate posture of Affairs: King <hi>John</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Recruits or Money could be obtained, departed from <hi>Warsaw</hi> on the 22th. of <hi>August</hi> towards the Frontiers, appointing a Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouz of that small Army he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:206299:60"/>had, to be held on the 15th. of <hi>September;</hi> they being not above 15 or 16000 Men Effective.</p>
               <p>'Tis true <hi>Romadanowski</hi> the <hi>Muscovitish</hi> General had a vast Army consisting of above 100 thousand Men, encamped near the River <hi>Dniester,</hi> but did little or no service with them, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the <hi>Turks,</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Suspicious, <hi>Jealous</hi> Nature of that People, caused Reports to be spread, that the <hi>Poles</hi> had made their own Terms, and were clapping up a <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>Port,</hi> without including or giving them notice of it; serving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of this Stratagem, the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> without any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable opposition had possessed themselves of the whole <hi>Ʋkrania,</hi> except two or three places, and at last besieged the Great City <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> which having assaulted with great fury, and the <hi>Muscovites,</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:206299:61"/>who promised to relieve it, being instead thereof on a sudden repas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the <hi>Dniester</hi> and Retreated, those of the Town surrendred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Articles to have their <hi>Lives and Goods saved;</hi> but the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Enemy without any regard to his capitulation, put all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and People that had fled thither from all parts round about for shelter, Men, Women, and Children to the Sword; so that of 100 <hi>thousand Souls</hi> very few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained alive within the space of few Hours.</p>
               <p>About the beginnning of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> the Troops of <hi>Lituania</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of about 12000 came up to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> so that then he was 30000 strong, and having held a Council of War at <hi>Slotzow</hi> on the Frontiers, resolved to March in the Head of them into the <hi>Ʋkrain</hi> and fall upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, casting aside all further Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:206299:61"/>which now again the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> (since his Master the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> had repassed the <hi>Danube</hi> on his return towards <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi>) had made overtures of, on purpose to amuse the <hi>Poles,</hi> and foment the Jealousies of the <hi>Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites,</hi> and so divide them.</p>
               <p>Accordingly his Majesty sending forth the <hi>Weywode</hi> of <hi>Russia</hi> with a considerable party to learn the Condition of the Enemy, who near the Walls of <hi>Caminiec</hi> surpriz'd and defeated 1000 <hi>Turkish</hi> Horse; and brought away 150 of them Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, did in Person march to <hi>Barr</hi> a City in the <hi>Ʋkrain,</hi> which he stormed so furiously that he soon became Master thereof: The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> that were there fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Castle, which proved not long their shelter, but on the 18 of <hi>Nov.</hi> was forced to surrender up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on discretion: The <hi>Turks</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty generously sent away with a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:206299:62"/>Convoy to <hi>Caminiec;</hi> but the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Tartars</hi> were distributed for purchase as <hi>Slaves</hi> amongst the Soldiers of <hi>Lithuania.</hi> Next his Victorious Majesty advanced to the City <hi>Mohilow</hi> on the <hi>Dniester,</hi> a place of great Importance, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>pass</hi> into <hi>Moldavia,</hi> which quickly surrendred to his Arms, as likewise did <hi>Sciana, Kalnick</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 40 other places of <hi>Podolia;</hi> but at this time the Forces of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania</hi> would needs leave his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and return home, alledging they were not able to bear the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of the season, it being now <hi>Dec.</hi> 74. but his Majesty with his gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Poles</hi> resolved still to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the Campaign, and push on his good Fortune, scarce a week passing, but some considerable Post or other was yielded to him; the <hi>Turks,</hi> tho they had very conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Forces in those parts not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to make Head against him.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:206299:62"/>
               <p> Towards the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> his Majesty took in <hi>Raskaw,</hi> a Considerable place on the <hi>Deinster,</hi> wherein were 1600 <hi>Turks,</hi> of whom the Foot were all Cut to pieces, but the <hi>Cavalry</hi> made their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape, the <hi>Polish</hi> Horse being so wearyed with continual Service, that they could not pursue them; So that now his Majesty had Subdued all that part of the <hi>Ʋkrain</hi> which lies Westward of the <hi>Neiper,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the City of <hi>Czebryn,</hi> the Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Dorosensko,</hi> whom He Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by a Treaty to Reduce to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the other made Shews of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying therewith, upon the Demands following, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That the <hi>Cossacks</hi> shall continue in the free Exercise of the <hi>Greek</hi> Religion, without any Disturbance what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever; 2. That a Bishop or Arch-bishop of their Church, shall have a place, and sit in the Senate; 3. That a part of the <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>krain</hi> shall be set apart for their Army. 4. That the King at his Coronation shall confirm all their Priviledges, and these Articles upon Oath; 5. That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick shall declare whether they have need of the Service of the <hi>Cossacks,</hi> and on what Conditions they desire it. 6. That the Deputies which the <hi>Cossacks</hi> shall send to the Dyet, shall be received, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:206299:63"/>with the same Respect as the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Dukedom of <hi>Lythuania,</hi> or of the Kingdom of <hi>Poland;</hi> 7. That they shall continue their Commerce with their Neighbours as heretofore: And Lastly, That they may Erect Printing-Houses, Schools, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But nothing Succeeded Effectually on these overtures, for <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensko</hi> was but Playing his own Game be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Poles</hi> and the <hi>Muscovites,</hi> and friend to neither, further than his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest led him.</p>
               <p>In <hi>April</hi> 75. The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in Numerous Bodies to take the Field. King <hi>John</hi> who had held out in those parts all the Winter without any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Recruits, whereby his small Army was much Weakned, so that it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believed he would be Necessitated to quit the <hi>Ʋkrain,</hi> yet Supported by his Natural Courage, he Resolv'd not to Stir a Foot, but on the last Extremity, and therefore Reinforc'd the Garrisons at <hi>Moh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>low, Nimirow, Braclaw, Kalmick,</hi> and <hi>Bialacierkiew;</hi> Which being done, he left not Forces enough to deserve the Name of an Army to keep the Field, had not his Valour and Conduct, like a Figure advanc'd in place in Arithmetick, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:206299:63"/>them Virtually as many thousands, as they were Numerally Hundreds.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May,</hi> the King made a Step to <hi>Zlok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zow,</hi> Eight Leagues from <hi>Leopold,</hi> where he had a Consultation with several Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Kingdom, Remonstrating to them the just Reason he had to Complain of being neglected, since after a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign of Seven Months, in which by an handful of Men so great Advantages had been procured to the Crown, by Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under its Obedience the greatest part of the <hi>Ʋkrain,</hi> and in which both his Majesty in his own Person, and all his Souldiers had Suffered so much through the Scarcity of Provisions they found in many places, being forc'd to eat Horses, Dogs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their Sustenance, together with Innumerable Fatigues and Dangers; Yet no Care had been taken at home to furnish him with Supplies Necessary, or to Enable him to Recruit his Army, which was now become so Weak as not to be longer able to keep the Field; His Majesty having hitherto been Necessitated to maintain the War almost wholly at his own Proper Charges; Which yet under all these Perplexities he Resolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:206299:64"/>
               <p> But whatever Instances he made, little was done towards his Supply; However, he return'd to the Army, and kept his Head Quarters at <hi>Leopold;</hi> And it was but high time to assure the People of those parts, by his Royal Presence, Who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise were just ready to abandon their Habitations, by Reason of those vast Swarms of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> which they had Intelligence were every day pouring into their Neighbourhood, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting in all, to the Number of 200 Thousand or upwards.</p>
               <p>On the 17th of <hi>August</hi> 1675. A Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was held of the Cheif Commanders of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> in the Presence of the Great <hi>Cham</hi> himself, and <hi>Ibrahim Bassa,</hi> where it was Resolved to Attempt, First, the Town of <hi>Slotskow,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to possess themselves of <hi>Leopol,</hi> where they understood the King of <hi>Poland</hi> then was Quarter'd, having not in all above 14000 men with him, for the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuanian</hi> Troops had not yet Join'd him. Pursuant hereunto, on the 22d of that Month <hi>Sultan Nuradin</hi> being on his March, with 40 Thousand Selected <hi>Tartars,</hi> the Flower of their whole Army; Accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed besides with the Eldest Son of <hi>Cham,</hi> and <hi>Sultan Aquigitary,</hi> and their Troops,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:206299:64"/>and many others of the most Eminent Officers, as <hi>Volunteirs,</hi> in this Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; So that the whole Body Consisted of at least Sixty Thousand; With which Formidable Force, <hi>Sultan Nuradin</hi> on the 23d early in the Morning appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Town and Castle of <hi>Slotskow,</hi> eight Leagues from the <hi>Polish</hi> Camp at <hi>Leopol.</hi> He immediately made an Assault, and continued it till two in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, with all Imaginable Fury; But the <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Russia</hi> who Commanded there, had so well disposed of his Men and of his Cannon, that with very little loss, he destroyed great Numbers of Infidels; who being thereby Extreamly discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, quitted their Enterprize, and Marched towards <hi>Leopol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where his Majesty having received Intelligence both of their Repulse at <hi>Slotskow,</hi> and of their Advance towards him, presently Ordered the Cannon to be continually Fired from the Castle, to give warning to all the Neighbouring Garrisons to be upon their Guard, then went and Visited the Camp, and gave the necessary Orders for the safety of his Queen and the young Princes, who were at the same time in that City; For he was Resolv'd to venture All in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:206299:65"/>of his Country, and Common Cause o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Christendom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Things being thus Setled, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty went up to an High Hill, from whence he could observe three Leagues Distance round about, and about Noon perceived by the Clouds of Dust that were raised, The Approach of the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The Kings Camp lay about a Mile from <hi>Leopol,</hi> on the East-side in a Valley shut up by several Hills, somewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Camp; that Way the Enemy was to approach, there was an Ascent of about 300 paces, and having Marcht as far on the top of the Hill, you descend again by a very narrow Way amidst a Wood that had lately been Cut, at the Bottom of which Descent there was a Plain by which the <hi>Tartars</hi> must neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily pass to Engage them: The King Commanded Prince <hi>Radzevil</hi> his Brother in Law, to Post himself with some Troops for the Guard of a Pass on the Right hand of his Camp; And General <hi>Karis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ki</hi> on the Left, caused several Pieces of Cannon to be planted on a Hill, from whence they might command the Plain through which the <hi>Tartars</hi> were to pass,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:206299:65"/>and Lined the Wood on each side of the Narrow Way with several Companies of Musqueteers; Then his Majesty caused some Troops of Horse with all the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers to advance into the Plain, to Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Enemy, who about four in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon appeared in such Numbers, that all the Plain was cover'd with them; In the mean time, the King from an Hill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd the Countenance of the Enemy, and gave the necessary Orders, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed several other Troops of Horse to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance before him, and being followed with Six Troops of <hi>Hussars,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> posted on the Right and Left of the Way, in the midst of the Copse or Low-wood, so advantagiously that they appeared to be far more in Number than indeed they were, his Majesty with a Natural Air of Gallantry usual to him in time of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a chearful Countenance Presag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Victory, Entred himself into the Plain, Encouraged his Souldiers, telling them he came there with a full Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either to Conquer with them, or to dye with them; and having thrice with a loud Voice pronounced by Way of Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the Name of JESUS, and giving the Souldiers all his Benediction, he brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Advanc'd in the Head of them toward
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:206299:66"/>the Enemy; And now the Fight began to be sharp on all sides, His Majesty omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no part of his Office either as to Courage or Conduct, but perform'd both the parts of a most prudent General, and of a most Valiant Souldier, and by his Example inspiring all the rest of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers, so that with this small handful of men, he made those vast Multitudes begin to fly before Night, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Numbers slain upon the place. And for a Testimony of a Compleat Victory, their Great and onely Standard which they always carry before them, was taken.</p>
               <p>His Majesty would gladly have pursued the Enemy further, but that the Night was dark, and he feared lest the <hi>Cham</hi> vvith the rest of the Troops might come up to their Assistance. In this great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the most Memorable Victory that has been Atcheived in our Age, or indeed almost in any other, the King had not vvith him above 4000 men (The rest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left to secure the City of <hi>Leopol,</hi>) and of those scarce 1500 came up to Execution; And vvith such a Party thus to defeat by plain downright fighting an Army of Threescore Thousand Combatants, seems altogether prodigious or miraculous; yet
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:206299:66"/>so great vvas the fright and Consternation that the Tartars vvere in, that they fled that one Night as many Leagues as they had Marched three days before, and to make the more hast, left behind them that little Baggage they had brought vvith them.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Confusion less in the Camps of the <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Ibrahim Bassa,</hi> upon see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Companions returning in this disorder from an expedition from which they had promised themselves so much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; But after some days Recruiting and Consideration, to shew that they were not dismaid at this ill success, 'twas resolved to March with all their Forces towards the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> And in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto, 2000 <hi>Janisaries</hi> and a strong body of Horse, were sent out to Attacque a small Castle near <hi>Brzeziani,</hi> in which were only 60 Poles, who yet so bravely Behaved themselves, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsed the Infidels with great loss; which so much dampt their Spirits, that they would not proceed on their intended de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign upon the City of <hi>Brzeziani.</hi> But on the contrary, the <hi>Polish</hi> Crown-Ensign, who Commanded there, making a Sally with a Party of Horse, fell upon the Rear of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> killed many of them,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:206299:67"/>and made the whole Body mend their pace.</p>
               <p>Soon after 10000 <hi>Tartars</hi> advancing somewhat near the City <hi>Leopol,</hi> the King sent out the Lord <hi>Harkownisky</hi> with a good Body of Horse against them, who after a brisk Engagement forced them to take to their heels; leaving a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber dead behind, tho in this Action there were several Brave <hi>Polish</hi> Gentlemen like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise slain.</p>
               <p>In <hi>September</hi> the <hi>Lithuanian Troops</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, the King was no longer content to make good his Post at <hi>Leopol,</hi> but would also with that small Army not then above 15000, advance to seek out the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who were at least seven times as many in Number. But left his Royal Consort, and the Young Princes still at <hi>Leopol,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing they should remain there, to keep the people of those parts in heart, who might otherwise for fear abandon their Habitations, and leave the Country desolate, but by this means were induced to continue at their Dwellings, consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the King, his Queen and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were exposed to the same danger as They.</p>
               <p>His Majesty understanding that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy had Besieged <hi>Podhais,</hi> did intend
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:206299:67"/>to March on the 15th of <hi>September</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive it, but on the 14. received Intelligence of its being Surrendred, and Twelve Thousand Persons made Prisoners, and the Town first plundred and then Burnt, though they had expresly Capitulated to March away with their Persons and Goods. Upon Advice of which, His Majesty on the 17th, held a Council of War at <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> where several of the Senators ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised not to Adventure with so few For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces against such a Mighty Enemy; But His Majesty Heroickly told them, That he would not sit still and see so many poor Christians carried into Slavery, and his Territories laid desolate; But was resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to Remedy it, or perish in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. And so Marched forwards the same day towards the Enemy; who were then sat down before <hi>Buczaez,</hi> but upon notice of his Advance, raised their Seige, and Marched with all their Forces to <hi>Trembowlae,</hi> which they Invested. And <hi>Ibrahim Bassa</hi> the Turks General, sent to summon the Garrison to surrender; who Answered, That if they came thither in hopes of meeting with any Booty or Plunder in the place, they were much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, For there were only Soldiers and Peasants who defended it, and had nothing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:206299:68"/>to lose but their Lives, which they were resolved to sell very dear. His Stout An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer much incensed the Turks, so that in 14 days which they continued the Seige, they shot above 2000 Cannon Bullets into the Town, and 500 Fireballs, and sprung divers Mines, though without effect, and stormed several times, but were repulsed with great loss, and yet continued obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to pursue the Siege, till happening by Chance to Intercept a Peasant charged with a Letter from the King to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, in which His Majesty assured him, That he was coming in Person with his whole Army to Relieve him, and that in order thereto he had already passed such a River, and was Marching directly towards the Enemy; Immediately upon which (such was the Terror of King <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bieski's</hi> name to the Infidels) <hi>Ibrahim Bassa</hi> gave order for dislodging the Cannon from the Batteries which consisted of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 100 peices, and to March towards <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and the next day decampt his whole Army and followed them; March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above Fifteen Leagues in so much Confusion and Consternation, that he Commanded the Tartars to keep near him to cover his March, just as if he had been routed in Battel, and a Victorious
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:206299:68"/>Enemy were in the pursuit of him; and thought themselves not secure till they had Entrencht themselves under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Canons of <hi>Caminiec;</hi> a thing almost incredible, that an Army of 15, or (at most) Sixteen Thousand should, force an Army of 100 Thousand and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to raise two Sieges with so much disorder and precipitation.</p>
               <p>Nay when lodged under the Walls of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniec,</hi> they yet thought not themselves safe; For the King advancing after them that way, <hi>Ibrahim Bassa</hi> held a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of War, where it was resolved not to stand an Engagement with the Poles, but to pass the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ester,</hi> and March away towards <hi>Walachia,</hi> which was done accordingly, but not so suddenly, but part of the Kings Troops under the Lord <hi>Lubomirski</hi> fell upon their Rear, and slew great Numbers of them.</p>
               <p>And also the King forthwith caused se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Troops to Advance one each side of the <hi>Niester,</hi> with such good success that the said. <hi>Lubomirsk</hi> seized on the Enemies Bridge, Cutting in pieces all those that were left to Guard it, and the Night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Lord <hi>Konski,</hi> General of the Artillery, met with 500 Waggons drawn by above 2000 Oxen, that were coming
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:206299:69"/>from <hi>Caminiec</hi> to pass that Bridge, which he took, destroying their Convoy, and releasing a great many Christians, whom the Infidels were carrying into Slavery; And the Soldiers being for their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement allowed the Plunder, possessed themselves of a rich booty, as well in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as goods, wherewith those Waggons were laden.</p>
               <p>His Majesty ordered that the Boats which Composed the Bridge before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, should be carried and laid up in some place of security, to be made use of as occasion should serve the next Spring. And then being informed, That the Turks in the fear they were in of being further pursued, had marched night and day, and again repassed the <hi>Danow,</hi> as also that the <hi>Tartars</hi> were returned home by the way of <hi>Bialogrod,</hi> resolved to put his Army into Winter Quarters, and to endeavour to settle Affairs at home, so as he might early take the Field next Spring. And accordingly His Majesty on the 12th of <hi>November,</hi> arrived at <hi>Zulk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew,</hi> three Leagues from <hi>Leopol,</hi> where, as he was most joyfully received of his Queen and the Young Princes his Children, so no less almost was the Joy of all the people, Crowding to behold, salute, and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:206299:69"/>home the Common Father and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer of their Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King Crowned; Obtains ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Victory over the</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Tartars; <hi>The Articles of Peace, The Magnificent Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of his Excellency the</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish <hi>Ambassador.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT was now high time to prepare for the Solemnity of the Kings Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for by the Constitution of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, there are several things which a Prince Elect cannot perform till that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony be past. Therefore <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. the Corps of the late King <hi>Michael Wisno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witski</hi> was Convey'd from <hi>Warsaw</hi> in a Chariot, drawn by Six Horses, attended with all the Officers of his Houshold, and many Persons of Quality, to <hi>Cracow,</hi> where their present Majesties were lately Arrived; Waited upon by almost all the Nobility of the Kingdom; The Body
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:206299:70"/>of King <hi>Casimire</hi> which had been sent for out of <hi>France,</hi> was also brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and on one and the same day were perform'd the Funerals of both those Kings, with the usual Ceremonies and becoming Respects to their Memories: Which being Dispatcht, on the Second of <hi>February</hi> 1675/6. King <hi>John Sobieski,</hi> and his Queen, were Crowned in the Castle of <hi>Cracow,</hi> with all the Pomp and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence Imaginable, and the next day his Majesty Received the Homage of all the Senators, Nobility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador presented to his Majesty a Solemn Declaration of the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, by which he Adopted the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> his Daughter, Declaring that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly She should upon all Occasions be lookt upon and Treated as a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>France;</hi> And on the eighth of <hi>March</hi> following her Majesty was happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered of a Young Princess. The King Applying himself to Supply the <hi>Vacancies,</hi> made the Prince <hi>Lubomirski</hi> Grand Marshal of the Kingdom; The Lord <hi>Siniawski Mareschal</hi> of the Court; on Prince <hi>Demetrius Wisnowiski,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Belz,</hi> He bestow'd the Command of General of the Forces of the Kingdom; and that of Lieutenant General, void
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:206299:70"/>by his Removal on <hi>Jablownowski</hi> Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of <hi>Russia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>June</hi> 76. the <hi>Sultan Nuradin</hi> with the two Sons of the <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary,</hi> pass'd the <hi>Niester</hi> with a great Body of Men, and sent out parties to Ravage the Country; And <hi>Ibrahim Bassa</hi> with his <hi>Turks</hi> Advanced to several Posts about <hi>Caminiac.</hi> In the mean time, tho' very good Resolutions were taken at the last Diet, yet so negligent had they been in the several Palatinates to put them in Execution, that the King had neither men nor money to make Resistance: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he Ordered what Troops he had to March towards <hi>Leopol,</hi> to a <hi>Rendezvous</hi> there; And being destitute of all other means, Issued out his Letters fot Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Arrierban</hi> for the Defence of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>About <hi>August</hi> 76. His Excellency <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> Ambassador from the King of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> to his Majesty of <hi>Poland,</hi> being Arrived at <hi>Dantzick;</hi> the Queen of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> soon after came thither also in her Way for <hi>France,</hi> to Drink the Waters of <hi>Burbon</hi> for the Recovery of her Health, (though afterwards that Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was laid aside) of whom he had
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:206299:71"/>Audience; and having performed his Complement to her Majesty, presented the Young Princess, to whom his Majesty of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> was prayed to be God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, with a very rich and Noble Jewel on the part of his said Majesty, and so passed on to <hi>Poland;</hi> Where he was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with all Demonstrations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and Kindness, suitable to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Person.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> began now to appear very formidable, and yet continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so sensible of their last years defeats, and so afraid of the very Name of King <hi>Sobieski,</hi> That they desired nothing more than Peace, for which purpose the Grand Seignior by the Prince of <hi>Moldavia</hi> made an Overture for a Treaty; Nor vvere the King of <hi>Polands</hi> Affairs in a Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to refuse such an Offer, and so Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners were sent. In the mean time to omit nothing for the publick safety, the King understanding that the <hi>Turks</hi> were on their March towards <hi>Jaslovies,</hi> about Six Leagues beyond <hi>Caminiec;</hi> He Marched on the sixth of <hi>September</hi> from <hi>Javarow</hi> with intention to Releive it, but by the Cowardice or Treachery of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the same was yielded with little or no resistance, and Burnt, as likewise they
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:206299:71"/>did two or three other considerable pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and were Marching towards <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowla.</hi> Whereupon His Majesty vvith all Expedition Advanced, and leaving all his <hi>Baggage</hi> at <hi>Zorawno</hi> to make more haste, on the 24th of <hi>October</hi> fell upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Vanguard, and killed many, putting the rest into disorder; but the <hi>Tartars</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 30 Thousand strong, Rallied, and came down on the whole <hi>Polish</hi> Army, where a bloody Fjght continued from Noon till Evening, and in conclusion the Infidels were put to flight in great Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; but His Majesty being vastly inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in Number, not above 15 or 16000 to oppose near 150 Thousand, had abundance of brave men Killed and Wounded.</p>
               <p>These ill Successes on the <hi>Turks</hi> part the more easily disposed them to a Peace, which soon after was Concluded on the following Articles, very honourable and advantagious to the <hi>Polish</hi> Crown, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Treaties concluded with the late King <hi>Michael,</hi> should be quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished, and no more account in the least be had of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That as for what concern'd <hi>Podolia,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> should retain <hi>Caminiec,</hi> with a certain Circuit of Ground round it; and concerning the <hi>Ʋkrain</hi> the greatest part,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:206299:72"/>as <hi>Bialacirkew, Pawloz, Galnick, Memocrow, &amp;c.</hi> to be quitted to the Poles; so that what was left to the <hi>Turks</hi> was inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and mostly under <hi>Dorosensko.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. All Prisoners and Slaves to be set at Liberty, and no further Hostility to be permitted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Christian Religion to be freely Exercised in all places that the <hi>Turks</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by this Treaty.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Turks</hi> should Renounce their pretentions to the Monies promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them by the Treaty of <hi>Leopol,</hi> and the <hi>Hostages</hi> given on that Account to be Released.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> should promise a strict Alliance to the Poles, and assist them against their Enemies.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the Custody of the Holy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre shall be restored to the <hi>Francis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi> to prevent all differences on that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>The Peace being thus happily conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the Infidels retired; His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of <hi>Poland</hi> came back in <hi>November</hi> to <hi>Zulkiew,</hi> where His Excellency my Lord <hi>Hide</hi> the <hi>English</hi> Ambassador had Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in a most splendid manner, being Conveyed in the Kings Richest Coach,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:206299:72"/>and received by the Mareschal of the Court at the Stairs, who Conducted him to the Chamber of Presence, where His Majesty received him standing under a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich Canopy of State, Cloathed in a long Robe of Cloth of Gold, and a Vest of Cloth of Silver. After the usual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of the Audience were over, and that the King had for some time enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained His Excellency in more familiar discourses, He was pleased to take him into the Queens Apartment, His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency every where meeting with a Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion full of the highest Kindness and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem from their Majesties, who as a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther instance thereof, were pleased to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite His Excellency to an Extraordinary Supper prepared in a large and stately Room, His Excellency being seated on the Kings Right-hand, and next to him, as likevvise on the Queens Left-hand se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral persons of the greatest Quality in that Kingdom. After Supper, vvhich lasted several Hours, and vvas served in vvith great Magnificence, His Excellency vvas Conducted back to his place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence with the King Coaches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The next day all the Senators and other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality made their Visits to His Excellency, vvhich he returned the day
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:206299:73"/>follovving; And on the 13th of <hi>November</hi> had his Audience of <hi>Congee</hi> of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties, in Order to his Return home. He hastening to <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> where he assisted as one of the Plenipotentiares for mediating a General Peace.</p>
               <p>In <hi>December</hi> following, His Most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Majesty in Testimony of his Respects to His Majesty Commanded his Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Resident in that Court to invest His Majesty with the Order of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> which Ceremony was performed with extraordinary Magnificence; The said Ambassador at the same time, making to both their Majesties several Presents from the King his Master, which were valued at some millions of Livres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:206299:73"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Actions of his Majesty of</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>afterwards; and Particularly in his late Expedition for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Empire, at the Raising of the Siege of</hi> Vienna, <hi>and since to this Time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HIS Majesty of <hi>Poland</hi> having thus Restor'd Peace to his Dominions, than which after such long Confusions and Hazards nothing could be more welcome or advantagious to his Subjects, did not during that Repose, abandon Himself to private Pleasures, nor at all Slacken his Royal Care for the publick Welfare and their Future Security: But applyed himself with all Dilligence to Repair those Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions which the late Incursions from abroad, and Disturbances at home, had made upon the Realm. To provide for the due and equal Administration of Justice, and placing fit Persons in Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Importance, and for the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Weighty Affairs: To Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:206299:74"/>and put a period to those Factions which had been nourished amongst the Grandees, by the secret Enemies of that Crown; To fortify himself with such ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Alliances as might conduce to the Common Utility of <hi>Christendom;</hi> and in a word, accommodating his Vigilant En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to all those prudential Arts of Government that render a people safe and happy, and are in themselves no less laudable and necessary Offices of a good Prince, though perhaps not so fam'd and glittering as the Atcheivments of Warr and Trophies of Victory.</p>
               <p>Amongst the rest he entred into a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muscovy,</hi> which held a long time for the Adjustment of several points in debate; for though they ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly pressed him to a New Rupture with the <hi>Port,</hi> offering great Assistances, yet His Majesty reflecting how much they had fail'd formerly in their promises of that kind, was cautious of embarquing himself in a new War without sufficient security that he should not still be left in the lurch when he might have most occasion to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the aid of their Forces.</p>
               <p>But in the beginning of the year 1683. Intelligence daily arriving of the vast preparations the <hi>Turks</hi> were making for
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:206299:74"/>Invading <hi>Hungary</hi> and other Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Parts of the Empire; His Majesty thought he could no longer in Prudence for his own Safety, Nor in Conscience for the general Cause of <hi>Christendom,</hi> sit any longer still without endeavouring to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Designs of the Infidels.</p>
               <p>And therefore caused a Diet to be held in <hi>February,</hi> where the matter being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, It was concluded, That Twenty Thousand Men should be forthwith rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Defence and Security of that Kingdom in the Present Conjuncture; And that the said Resolution should stand good tho' the Dyet should happen to be unseasonably broken up through the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi> of any of the Deputies, which too often happens.</p>
               <p>And Count <hi>Wallastain</hi> being sent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador from his Imperial Majesty to the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> did on the second of <hi>April,</hi> 1683. Conclude and Sign an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, whereby the Emperour obliged himself to Act with an Army of Sixty Thousand Men against the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> promised to have between Thirty and Forty Thousand Men in the Field the Summer following for the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Empire; Which League was approved of by the Dyet, who on
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:206299:75"/>the fourth of that Moneth broke up their Assembly with great satisfaction to all Parties.</p>
               <p>There was at that time a <hi>Turkish Chiaux</hi> present in the <hi>Polish</hi> Court, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured all he could to divert His Majesty from entering into this Engagement, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that the <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary</hi> with a mighty Army would fall into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if any Assistance were given the Emperour from thence. And it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so reported, as if the Minister of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Christian King was not wanting also underhand to cast in Rubs to hinder His Majesty from those Resolutions. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, so it was, that the Threatnings of the one, &amp; Insinuations of the other were not regarded, but His Majesty remain'd still stedfast in his purpose of opposing the Progress of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Arms; which Pious Inclinations, the Justice of Heaven has since Rewarded with such stupendious Successes, as must render his Name and Memory the delight and wonder of all Posterity.</p>
               <p>I shall neither weary the Reader with a tedious deduction of the Original Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions and Progress of the disturbances in <hi>Hungary,</hi> begun at first by several Great Men of that Kingdom <hi>(Roman Catholicks)</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:206299:75"/>on pretence of their Liberties being vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and afterwards unhappily continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fomented by the unnecessary Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities practised upon the Protestants of that Country; Which the <hi>Turk</hi> taking the Advantage of, offered them his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and on that quarrel seemed to ground his present Expedition; Nor shall I undertake to give a particular Account of that most memorable Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> since the same is sufficiently publisht to the World by other Pens; But briefly summ up the most remarkable passages wherein His Majesty of <hi>Poland</hi> was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
               <p>The Intelligence of the <hi>Turks</hi> Advance with a vast Army, extreamly startled the Emperour, the rather for that at the same time, He had Advice that the <hi>French</hi> were drawing together great Forces towards <hi>Germany;</hi> So that he was under Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions they would have taken the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this Juncture to fall upon the Empire on that side; But whether it were an effect of the <hi>Generosity</hi> of the most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King, or that he omitted it on the earnest <hi>Request of the Pope,</hi> who wrote to him on that occasion, or that he waited to <hi>see first</hi> the success of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Arms, or for whatever other Reasons, so
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:206299:76"/>it was, That he attempted nothing of that kind.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Imperial Army</hi> under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> had Besieged <hi>New-Hausel</hi> (a strong Town taken some years since from the Empire by the <hi>Turks</hi>) where they had advanced with good hopes of being quickly Masters of it, when ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Order came from the Emperour to Raise that Seige, and put Forces into <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra, Raab,</hi> and <hi>Presburgh,</hi> esteemed the Bulwarks of <hi>Christendom,</hi> and which it was rationally supposed the <hi>Turks</hi> would first Attempt, and not leave behind them Garrisons of such Importance; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great Care was taken to fortify them, whilst the Imperial City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> not looking upon it self in such sudden dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, was not so well provided for.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> used all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of a prudent General to secure his Retreat from <hi>Newhausel;</hi> but his Forces were so discouraged at the Raising of the Siege, that when the Infidels from the Garrison fell upon them, the <hi>Rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard</hi> made little opposition, but hastned their March to save themselves, and so exposed the Infantry, which the Duke had placed behind in certain Houses to Flank the Enemy, to inevitable destruction, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:206299:76"/>whom was the Count <hi>de Taexis,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended of one of the best Families in <hi>Spain.</hi> The Duke with the rest of the Army retreated towards the Isle of <hi>Schut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time the Troops intrusted with the Guard of an important Pass at <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ag,</hi> revolted to Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> Chief of the <hi>Malecontents</hi> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Confederate with the <hi>Turks,</hi> who thereby finding the way open, past the <hi>Vaag,</hi> and advanced to the Banks of the <hi>Danube;</hi> and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Bridge above <hi>Papas,</hi> carried over their Infantry, whilst their Cavalry and Baggage Marched round, and came over the Bridge at <hi>Papas</hi>-Town, and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sent out Parties which Harrassed and Plundred and Burnt all the Country; And one great Detachment following the Imperial Army fell upon their Reer, who by the suddenness of the Enemies coming, and the Bruit of their vast Numbers, were so amaz'd, that notwithstanding all the Duke could do, his Cavalry aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned his Foot, and retired towards <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna;</hi> and though the Chevalier of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> (Son of the late Count of <hi>Soissons</hi>) and Count <hi>Taaff,</hi> made a brave resistance, (wherein the <hi>Former</hi> was slain) yet the <hi>Turks</hi> became Master of the Baggage, and therein of a <hi>Booty</hi> valued at Three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:206299:77"/>Thousand Crowns. The greatest part of the Dukes Infantry secured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the <hi>Isle</hi> of <hi>Schut,</hi> and were in eminent hazard of being all lost, had not the Duke quickly brought back his Horse, and forc'd a passage to their Relief, and put part of them (as ordered before) into <hi>Raab, Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Presburgh,</hi> and with the rest and his <hi>Cavalry</hi> withdrew near <hi>Vienna;</hi> For which Cities-sake this disaster may be counted happy, for if these Forces had not been thus driven thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it would not have been able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it self against the unexpected Siege which immediately followed.</p>
               <p>For upon Advice of this near approach of the Enemy, Their Imperial Majesties and the Court, on the 7th of <hi>July,</hi> left <hi>Vienna,</hi> and went thence to <hi>Lintz,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Passaw;</hi> but before they were gone far from the City, had the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to behold all the Towns, Villages and Houses on the other side the <hi>Danube</hi> on Fire by the Enemy, who wherever they came gave those <hi>Flaming.</hi> Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their Cruelty.</p>
               <p>Soon after the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> thought fit also to retire with his Cavalry, and what Forces he could spare, leaving there under the Governour Count <hi>Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:206299:77"/>Twelve Thousand Men Effective, which with the Standing Garrison com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated the whole to about Fifteen Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Souldiers, besides the <hi>Scholars, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghers,</hi> and <hi>Handicrafts-men,</hi> who were able to bear Arms, and did continual duty.</p>
               <p>On the fourteenth of <hi>July</hi> the City was <hi>Invested</hi> by the <hi>Turkish</hi> Army, consisting in all of about 150 Thousand Men, against which most Formidable Power, and all their Attaques, wherein they were not wanting either in <hi>Courage</hi> or <hi>Skill,</hi> but did more mischief by their <hi>Mines</hi> than their <hi>Batteries,</hi> the Garrison though but ill provided, did yet by the Resolution and Encouragement of their <hi>Incomparvble Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> bravely defend it self, till the twelfth of <hi>September</hi> following, during all that time doing great Execution on the Enemy, who were then beat off by the United Forces of the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and the Imperial Princes.</p>
               <p>For pursuant to the League with the Emperour before mentioned, No sooner was it known, That the Infidels were Entred <hi>Christendom,</hi> but His Majesty of <hi>Poland</hi> with all imaginable diligence ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together his Forces: And though there wanted not some about him vvho
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:206299:78"/>were supposed Pensioners to <hi>France,</hi> That insinuated how unsafe it might be to the Kingdom, for its Forces to March out to assist others, when in the mean time they might be liable to the Incursions of the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> at home; yet this brave Prince esteemed himself obliged in <hi>Justice and Honour</hi> to neglect such Suggestions, and with all Expedition put his Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a posture to March. And having dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht away the <hi>Sieur Lubomirski</hi> with three Regiments of Horse, before, who notwithstanding Count <hi>Teckeley's</hi> Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to Intercept them, joyned with General <hi>Schuts,</hi> and did very good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in several Rencounters, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty in Person came to <hi>Cracow</hi> on the 29th of <hi>July,</hi> having first been to perform his Devotions at <hi>Crenstochow,</hi> And soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter advanc'd with his whole Army, through <hi>Silesia,</hi> causing it to March in three Bodies, and different ways, for their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Conveniency and Speed; And from the Imperial Court the <hi>Schafgats</hi> vvas ordered to go and Complement him at his Arrival on the <hi>Frontiers,</hi> also his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Majesty Himself on the twenty third of <hi>August</hi> parted from <hi>Passaw</hi> for <hi>Krembs,</hi> where was appointed the Common Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous for His Majesty of <hi>Poland,</hi> the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:206299:78"/>Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and the Auxiliary Troops of the Empire, all to meet at.</p>
               <p>On the second of <hi>September</hi> His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of <hi>Poland</hi> Arrived at <hi>Holbron</hi> with the bravest Cavalry that the Sun ever beheld, (but much Harrassed with the fatigues of so tedious and continual a March) consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 18000. Horse, most of them <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Gentlemen, who for the most part had each of them a stout Servant or Two well Arm'd; His Infantry were about 15000, and could not come up till two or three days after, so that there was a Necessity to rest a few days to Refresh the wearied Souldiers before they adventured on any Action: For which purpose the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had provided against their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming great quantities of Provisions both for Horse and Men.</p>
               <p>In which time, as well the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> as their Highnesses of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Saxony</hi> came to visit and pay their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects to <hi>His Majesty,</hi> who received them after a most obliging manner, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented his Son Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> to their Acquaintance and Friendship; a Prince not above Fifteen or Sixteen Years of Age, but in prudence and Courage much
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:206299:79"/>out stripping his years, who attended his Father this Campaign, to instruct him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self under so great a Master in the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of War.</p>
               <p>After the first <hi>Civilities</hi> necessary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Persons of such Illustrious Quality were past, knowing their Business was not Complement, but the <hi>Securing of Christendom</hi> from the most Eminent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it had been in, for some Centuries; They held <hi>a Council of War</hi> to adjust the measures fit to be taken in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that great Work before them, viz. <hi>The Relief of</hi> Vienna; And having Concluded all Particulars, and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the Scheme of their Resolutions to the Emperour (who had altered his Intention of Coming up to the Armies, because he would leave the Honour of Commander in Chief to the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) and the same being by him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; They began to Advance to put them in Execution; and indeed it was <hi>High time;</hi> For the City was now reduc'd to the very last Extremity, and in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane probability could not have held out for many hours longer.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:206299:79"/>
               <p> On the 11th of <hi>September,</hi> The whole Christian Army, consisting of near Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score thousand Combatants, was come almost within sight of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and all things were prepared for the Battel next Day.</p>
               <p>The Right Wing was assign'd by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to his Majesty of <hi>Poland,</hi> because He had most Horse, and the Country was on that side open; The Left to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> for that it was amongst Inclosures all along the <hi>Danube<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> And the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body to the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> with the Troops of the Circles.</p>
               <p>By break of Day, <hi>September</hi> 12. All the Generals met on an Hill to give the last Orders, and were no sooner come thither, But a Body of about ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of the Flower of the Turkish Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appeared, advancing amain towards the Christians; whereupon a Battalion was Ordered to put themselves into a Vineyard that was on another Hill, hard by, seconded by three other Battalions, who put a stopp to the Turks Carrier; for not induring the fierce Firings of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:206299:80"/>said Battalions, and being all Horse, and in a Ground where they could not well Attaque the Foot, they contented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with <hi>one Discharge</hi> accompanied with an <hi>Hideous Noise</hi> or <hi>Hollow,</hi> and so retired. Whereupon the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and other Princes, drew the Army in <hi>Three Lines,</hi> all closed, without any Intervails, charging them to March very flowly towards the Enemy, and to <hi>stand</hi> when the Turks came to Charge them, keep themselves close, and not <hi>Fire</hi> till the Enemy had made their Discharge; which was observ'd accordingly. The Turks advanced towards them with a <hi>horrible Cry,</hi> as if they meant to break in upon them, hoping thereby to make them give way, or put them into Disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But perceiving that the Christians <hi>stood firm,</hi> and expected them in a very close Order; They durst not push any further, but made an Halt, Discharg'd and wheeld off; Upon which immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately all the first Line of the Christians <hi>Fired,</hi> and the whole Army advanced with a slow pace, gaining Ground upon the Enemy; who returning, came up as before, and the Christians thereupon made an Halt, and expected them; and the Turks having Discharged, again
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:206299:80"/>retired; and thus they did several times without being able to break in upon the Christians, who still gain'd Ground and drave them before them. Being thus got near the Enemies <hi>Camp,</hi> a Body of Foot and Dragoons was Detached to Attacque their <hi>Cannon,</hi> which they became Masters of without much Opposition, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my having but a small number of Foot to defend them. On the Right Wing their Horse endeavoured to Charge the Christians in <hi>Flank,</hi> but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> mistrusting their Design, caused part of the second Line to Advance and make <hi>a Front</hi> on that side, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Enemy <hi>in Person</hi> with the first Line made them give way.</p>
               <p>Whilst this was doing, the <hi>Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier</hi> had caused two Mines to be sprung under the <hi>Ramparts</hi> of the City not farr from the <hi>Scots-Gate,</hi> whereby a Breach was made able to let in Thirty or Forty Men <hi>a Breast;</hi> designing to take the City <hi>by storm,</hi> and instantly to draw his Men within the <hi>Walls,</hi> and under the Cannon thereof to secure his Baggage Tents and Train. But tho' his Forces designed to Effect this, omitted nothing that could be done, and fought like men
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:206299:81"/>Desperate, rather than Valiant; yet Count <hi>Starembergh</hi> having instantly clapt ten Great Guns upon the Breach loaden with Musquet Shot, Nails, pieces of Horse-Shoes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cut off the Assai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants in vast Numbers, and yet fresh ones still Crowded on, and were as Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly resisted by the Besieged, so that the Ground for above half an hour was Disputed with the last Efforts of <hi>Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> on each side; but at last the Turks were forced to Retreat to their Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; Upon whom <hi>Starembergh</hi> made a sally; and a party from the Prince of <hi>Lorrain</hi> coming at that instant to his Assistance on the other side, beat them out, and Cut in pieces more than Four Thousand <hi>Janizaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Conclusion towards Night the whole Body of the Turks began to fly, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians pursuing them beyond their Camp, being too weary, after having been near Forty-eight hours upon Duty, to follow them; But the Soldiers were Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>pain of Death</hi> not to stirr out of their Ranks, and the whole Army continued all night in Battalia to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any surprize. But the next Day finding the Enemy clear March'd away,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:206299:81"/>Liberty was given to Plunder their Camp, half a Company going out at a time, while the other half continued in Arms, and when the first return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Second went out in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Here were taken all the Enemies Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and vast quantities of Provisions and Ammunition, above one hundred pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cannon, two <hi>Horse-Tails</hi> (which they use to hang out as a Denunciation of Warr, when they undertake any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.) The Viziers own <hi>Horse,</hi> all their <hi>Tents,</hi> in Number above Thirty Thousand, and the <hi>Graud Seigniors</hi> STANDARD, Extraordinary Rich and Sumptuous; The Exact <hi>Figure,</hi> and <hi>Arabick Inscriptions</hi> whereof, with their <hi>Interpretations,</hi> you have before the Title-Page hereof.</p>
               <p>This mighty Victory (in obtaining which, the Christians lost not above One Thousand Men, and very few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality) must under God, be chiefly attributed to the great <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who Engaged his <hi>Royal Person</hi> amongst the thickest of the Enemy, having with him
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:206299:82"/>the Prince his Son, who thus early signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd Himself. Nor ought the Electors of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> to want their share of the Glory, since they all Behaved them selves extreamly well, and gained great Honour and Reputation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September</hi> the Thirteenth, The King of <hi>Poland</hi> and other Princes entered <hi>Vienna,</hi> a sad Spectacle of past desolation, which yet now served to Inhance the <hi>Joy</hi> for its delivery; His Majesty Embraced the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Starembergh</hi> with the highest expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of Esteem for his Person, Valour and Conduct. The next day the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Arrived there, and met the King of <hi>Poland</hi> at the Head of his Army drawn up in <hi>Battalia,</hi> to whom in the most En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing Terms, he made his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments; Who received them with a <hi>Modesty</hi> equal to his Courage; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing that he had only used <hi>his just en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to discharge the Obligations which he ow'd to the Safety and Repose of</hi> Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>and that the Success of his Arms, was to be wholly attributed to the Goodness of God, and the Bravery of those Princes who had done him the Honour to joyn their Treops to his.</hi> His Imperial Majesty having ordered
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:206299:82"/>Prince <hi>Alexaneer</hi> to be presented with a Sword richly set with Diamonds, and so after a short interview departed, and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> Decamped with his Army and marched to <hi>Wiseha,</hi> and so by a Bridg of Boats over the <hi>Danube</hi> about a mile below <hi>Presburgh,</hi> on the twenty fifth of <hi>September,</hi> and the twenty seventh the Imperial Army advancing after him pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed over at the same place.</p>
               <p>On the ninth of <hi>October,</hi> understanding that a Body of about 14000 <hi>Turks</hi> lay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd near <hi>Barkan,</hi> being the Choicest Troops that were remaining of their whole Army, under the Command of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Bassa's</hi> of best account, His Majesty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and some few of the <hi>Imperial</hi> Troops advanced thither, The <hi>Turks</hi> no sooner saw them, but they came briskly on, and Charged very desperately, but being as warmly received, after a sharp Encounter the Infidels were put to Flight, one of their <hi>Bassa's</hi> slain, another taken Prisoner, and the rest of them hurrying over the Bridge at <hi>Gran,</hi> the same broke down, so that of all that Body of men, there were not 4000. that escaped. In this Battel the young Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> had his Horse shot under him. Also here, the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:206299:83"/>brave <hi>Lord Landsdown,</hi> a young <hi>English</hi> Noblem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n (Son to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Bath</hi>) who being abroad upon his <hi>Travels</hi> with his Brother, had put himself into the <hi>Campaign,</hi> first as a <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntier,</hi> and at the Relief of <hi>Vienna</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a Captain of Horse, where having given large Testimonies of his Valour, he now Commanded a squadron in Count <hi>Taafts</hi> Brigade, and so signaliz'd himself. That afterwards about the beginning of <hi>January</hi> last, waiting on his Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty at <hi>Lintz,</hi> he was received with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular esteem in that Court, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour at his taking leave of him, vvas pleased to declare, that he <hi>could not suffer a Nobleman of so much merit to return for</hi> England, <hi>from a Compagne, wherein he had acquitted himself with so much Gallantry, without a Mark of Honour,</hi> and therefore at the same time delivered him a Warrant to the Elector of <hi>Mentz,</hi> Chancellour of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to pass a <hi>Diploma</hi> constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Lordship a Count <hi>of the Empire,</hi> by the Title of <hi>Count Greenville.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Considerable Exploit of his Majesty of <hi>Poland</hi> was, by taking of <hi>Zyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> a place of great Importance; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving parted with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:206299:83"/>and understanding that the <hi>Turks</hi> had there a Considerable Garrison, vvhich might Incommode the Communication between his Troops, and the <hi>Imperialists;</hi> sent the Prince his Son and the Palatine of <hi>Lublin</hi> with a small Body of Horse, to view it, and at their return, gave order to attaque that place; where the <hi>Turks</hi> on their side were in a posture of defence, and having notice that that the King had ordered the <hi>Cossacks</hi> to fall upon their Suburbs, set them on fire the night before, which yet hindred not the <hi>Cassacks</hi> from possessing themselves of one of their <hi>Gates,</hi> and breaking down the <hi>Paliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> defended themselves with great Resolution, and after a sharp dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute forced the <hi>Cossacks</hi> to retire, till being seconded with some fresh Troops, they renewed the Charge, and Compelled the <hi>Turks</hi> to quit the Town, and take shelter in the Castle, which the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded immediately to be Assaulted, and then the <hi>Turks</hi> hung out a <hi>White Flag,</hi> and the Commander in Chief with two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers came out, and prayed his Majesty to permit them to March out to <hi>Buda;</hi> Which was granted, and so they went forth, being eight hundred Foot and five hundred Horse; In the place were taken
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:206299:84"/>great store of Provisions and Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Twenty Pieces of Cannon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides several small Field Pieces; and His Majesty afterwards put the Town into the hands of the <hi>Imperialists;</hi> And the very next day sent to summon two Castles called <hi>Brigh</hi> and <hi>Holoch,</hi> who yielded at discretion. Thence his Majesty Marched to <hi>Kimasombat,</hi> and on the sixteenth of <hi>Novem.</hi> the General of <hi>Lithuania</hi> met his Majesty there.</p>
               <p>During his <hi>Majesties</hi> stay in the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> he endeavoured by all <hi>fair means</hi> to reduce Count <hi>Teckeley</hi> to obedience, offering him very good Termes, for the performance of which he would be <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty;</hi> but finding the same ineffectual, and that it would not be convenient to continue with all his Troops this Winter in those parts, left only those of <hi>Lithua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> there, and with the rest which had been much weakned by those extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and continual Services they had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, Marcht home into <hi>Poland?</hi> and Arrived at <hi>Cracow</hi> on the 21st of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> where he was welcomed by all the Applauses and Testimonies of an <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Affection</hi> from his Subjects; and to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:206299:84"/>render their Joys and Triumphs more Compleat, the News Arrived that the <hi>Sieur Kiniski</hi> General of the <hi>Cossacks,</hi> had obtained a Great Victory over the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> who being above forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand strong, Commanded by two <hi>Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Generals, and <hi>Haley Bey</hi> a <hi>Turkish Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer,</hi> who had under him a selected Body of <hi>Spahies,</hi> and some Troops of <hi>Janiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> had made a suddain March, design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fall upon the Poles in <hi>Podolia,</hi> and Relieve <hi>Caminiec,</hi> which was Blockt up; whereupon the General of the <hi>Cossiacks</hi> drawing together thirty thousand Men, and marching with great diligence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept them, on the fourth of <hi>December</hi> Attacqued them near <hi>Tilgrotin,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated them, with so great a slaughter, that thirty thousand men of them, were destroyed on the place, and in pursuit; Their two <hi>Tartar Generals</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring in vain to Rally their men, being slain, and <hi>Haley Bey</hi> being taken Prisoner, offered an hundred thousand Crowns for his Life, But the <hi>Cossacks</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whose hands he fell, quarrelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout sharing the money, <hi>Killed him,</hi> to end the dispute.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:206299:85"/>
               <p> After which Victory, the <hi>Cossacks</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd into the Countrey of the <hi>Tartars of Budziack,</hi> putting all they met with to the Sword; so that, 'tis said, they slew near one Hundred-Thousand; and having finisht their Ravage, took <hi>Bialogrod</hi> and <hi>Ketin,</hi> and placed Garrisons therein. All which successes made such Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions on the <hi>Wallachians,</hi> that Thirty Thousand of them have Sworn fidelity to the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> and to Joyn with the <hi>Cossacks</hi> against the Turks and Tartars; And 'tis said the <hi>Moldavians</hi> are following their Example. In the mean time His Majesty has appointed <hi>a Diet</hi> to be held for taking the Necessary Resolutions for prosecuting this Happy Warr; Resolving to be again in the <hi>Field</hi> early in the Spring with a greater Army than ever.</p>
               <p>Thus have we waited on this <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Prince</hi> through several of the most Important Actions of his Life; and now must leave him, for the present, to the Conduct of that Divine Hand which has hitherto blest him with such a constant series of miraculous <hi>Success.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Attempt his <hi>Character</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:206299:85"/>another Volumne; <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Caesar, Ʋnited,</hi> will not express half the <hi>Idaea</hi> of his Merit. He is Master of all the Gallantry of <hi>Antient Hero's,</hi> but free from the Blemishes of their <hi>Pride,</hi> Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and other <hi>Vices;</hi> His Subjects find Him as <hi>Just,</hi> kind and <hi>Indulgent,</hi> As his Enemies, <hi>Valiant;</hi> And he Labours not for his <hi>own Glory</hi> and Interest; But to Repel Barbarians, and secure and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the Bounds of <hi>Christianity;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his Name is become more terrible to the <hi>Infidels</hi> than ever was that of <hi>Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg</hi> or <hi>Huniades;</hi> In a word He seems a special Instrument raised by Providence to Conferr <hi>a double Obligation</hi> on all the Christian World, by Repulsing the <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> from without, and preventing the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of others amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, who from an <hi>Insatiate Ambition,</hi> are more than suspected of a Design to have taken the Advantage by those Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions, to have Grasp'd to themselves an <hi>Ʋniversal</hi> Monarchy.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:86"/>
            <head>Advertisemtnt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucians</hi> Works, Translated from the Greek, by <hi>Ferrand Spence,</hi> the Second Vollumn is in the Press, and will be Published in few Days.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:86"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:206299:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:206299:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:206299:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:206299:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:206299:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:206299:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:206299:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:206299:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:206299:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:206299:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:206299:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:206299:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:206299:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:206299:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:206299:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:206299:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:206299:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:206299:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:206299:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:206299:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:206299:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:206299:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:206299:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:206299:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:206299:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>